<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
            <author>Pierse, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102573</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838345</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1113:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
                  <author>Pierse, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Redcrosse Streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E(-E8).</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Some leaves stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cheyne, Joan, --  Lady, d. 1614.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VERTVES ANATOMIE. <hi>OR</hi> A COMPENDIOVS DESCRIPTION OF THAT late Right Honorable, Memorable, <hi>and Renowned Bedfordſhire Lady,</hi> the Lady CHEANY, of <hi>Tuddington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By CHARLES PIERSE.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling in Red-croſſe Streete. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS, AND TRVELY RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady, the Lady CROFTS, wife to that <hi>worthy Knight Sir</hi> IOHN CROFTS, <hi>all</hi> health and proſperity in this world, <hi>and eternall ioy and felicitie in</hi> the world to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT worſhipfull, or rather Right worthy Lady: the title of the former, being made more il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious by the fruition of the latter. For honours and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are not the precedent cauſe of vertue, but vertue of them: I haue, I feare, aſſumed too much vpon me, and broken the bounds of that old prouerbe; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſutor vltra cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitum:</hi> yet, worthy Lady, on whoſe fauourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not on my owne deſerts, I altogether rely: doe humbly craue your Ladiſhips moſt gratious protection, to ſhelter me from thoſe maligna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which might oppoſe themſelues againſt me: I know it wants that beautie, hue, and amiable aſpect, which ſhould externally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne it, and make it pleaſing in your eyes. Yet if your Ladiſhip pleaſe to take a view of the inward truth and
<pb facs="tcp:2720:3"/>
ſincere deuotion of the heart, it may proue as true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, though not ſo fairely featured as the reſt. For as it is in nature, ſo it is in arte, much vice may lie hid in faire complexions, and much hypocriſie in arte. I ſpeake not this, good Lady, to derogate ought from learned Arts, or worthy wits inriched with eloquence, whereby my impoueriſhed and naked lines ſhould bee clothed with their garments; but that I feare the hard ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſures of theſe ill ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times, as much as I hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſome fauorable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruction fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your worthy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>If any put out a <hi>Quaere,</hi> and aske me why I wrote this booke, I could alledge many reaſons: but I ceaſe to erect too large a portall to ſo ſmall a ſtructure; I had rather my booke ſhould be abſtracted then detracted. Giue me leaue therfore, rather in few words to expreſſe what I would, then in many what I could ſpeake. Since ſo many, whoſe loues depend vpon your Ladiſhips de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts, doe offer vp gifts, a teſtimony of the loue they owe, which haue of long time knowne your moſt free and gentle diſpotions, and ſeene the vertuous inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your minde. I could not chuſe, nor in common Chriſtianitie do any leſſe, if no other bound affection, nor duetie had moued me, but ſhew ſome thankfulnes with the rest, though ſatisfaction I cannot giue with the beſt. I haue therefore preſumed to preſent vnto your Ladiſhip, not ſuch as your honor doth deſerue, or as I deſire, or as my duety and the ſubiect of my booke doe require, but ſuch as my ſmall ability, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilitie,
<pb facs="tcp:2720:3"/>
could prepare to offer vnto you: for hauing no need of externall gifts, I giue the internall gifts of the minde, as a free thought, a lame ſacrifice not worthy to be recorded with thoſe great ones, which could caſt aboue a widowes mite into the treaſurie, or offer vp vnto their maſter more then a cup of cold water. Reade it, moſt pious Ladie, if ought be in it worthy the leaſt reſpect or fauour, it is not mine, but her honors and your Ladiſhips, from whoſe moſt pure &amp; eminent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues this dimme and darke candle of mine tooke her firſt light. Some may hold it a diſparagement to her honor, becauſe <hi>eſt ab indigno,</hi> others may iudge I write truely, but not ſufficiently, both are right: for ſilent duety, though in it ſelfe it is commendable, yet in reſpect of others, it winnes more loue being actiue, <hi>laus virtutis actio;</hi> and for the other, what my weake skill doth deny, yet my vrging will ſupply: <hi>vltra poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe non eſt eſſe.</hi> What ſhould I ſpeake of your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips free and bounteous diſpoſition? What ſhould I ſpeake of thoſe ornaments and graces you are both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly &amp; outwardly indued with? which with as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tongues as <hi>Argus</hi> had eyes, ſpread abroad your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued worth, that I cannot tel whether our ſoyle more iuſtly admires you, or inwardly deſires you:
<q>
                  <l>Where vertuous life, faire children, happie ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Doe all concurre to make you fortunate,</l>
                  <l>And whereas many will hereafter minde you,</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in the iſſue that you left behinde you,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2720:4"/>In which moſt fruitfull buds as may out-liue you,</l>
                  <l>Your worth and yours a double life may giue you,</l>
                  <l>Where though your ſoule had reacht eternitie,</l>
                  <l>Your name on earth may liue and neuer die.</l>
               </q>
So thriue faire Lady, and flouriſh euer in thoſe faire pathes of vertue, that as it was a bleſſing to <hi>Dauid</hi> that one of his ſeed did inherite his earthly Throne, ſo it may be a greater bleſſing to your Ladiſhip, that many of your ſeed, ſhould inherite the Throne eternall. It was not ſo great a glory for <hi>Salomon</hi> to inherite his Fathers Kingdome, as his Fathers holineſſe and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: Then how much, Madam, may you reioyce in ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that yours enioy not onely much temporall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and bleſsings, but alſo are indued with many gifts and graces of the Spirit, great louers of vertue, and imbracers of true religion and piety. Long may they ſo continue to your Ladiſhips full ioy. Long may they all liue and grow old in honors and vertues, and with that Poet euer wiſh:
<q>
                  <l>Fortunati omnes, ſi quid mea carmina poſſunt:</l>
                  <l>Nulla dies vnquam memori vos eximet aeuo.</l>
               </q>
Thus humbly intreating your good Ladiſhip to accept this my firſt and meane labour, vnder whoſe wings it moſt hopefully truſts, I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours all too meane, and farre vnworthy ſeruant, but not leaſt deuoted,</hi> Charles Pierſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD, THE LORD WENTWORTH.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen meannes ſpeakes, and honors balance weighes him:</l>
            <l>Had need ſpeake well, for feare his tongue betrayes him</l>
            <l>Leſt vndiſcerning, there diſcouered lies</l>
            <l>Some marke of folly to iudicious eies.</l>
            <l>Euen ſo, great Lord, my timerous quill proceeds</l>
            <l>Much like a ſcholler, that his leſſon reades</l>
            <l>Before his awfull maſter, trembling ſtill</l>
            <l>Whether vnkind he ſaid it well or ill.</l>
            <l>So like that pupill I the liſts doe enter,</l>
            <l>More bold then wiſe to giue the perilous venter:</l>
            <l>And cannot tell what dangers may enſue,</l>
            <l>Did not I hope much honor lay in you.</l>
            <l>Not like that <hi>Fortunes</hi> brood, whoſe ayrie ſpirits</l>
            <l>Doe mount them <hi>Icarus</hi>-like aboue their merits,</l>
            <l>Where when their flight's at higheſt riſe of all,</l>
            <l>The Sunne doth melt their wings, and then they fall:</l>
            <l>Or like <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> who did fondly looke</l>
            <l>On his owne ſhadow in a cryſtall brooke,</l>
            <l>And doting on't, ſtept neerer to haue kiſt it,</l>
            <l>Where he fell in, and drown'd himſelfe, yet miſt it.</l>
            <l>Euen ſo this world which theſe faire ſtreames behold,</l>
            <l>Build their attempts vpon ſuch hopes too bold,</l>
            <l>Making the droſſie ſubſtance of this earth,</l>
            <l>The greateſt cauſe of honor and of birth:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:5"/>Some louing honors ſo, buy them, to make them:</l>
            <l>Better contented they, that can forſake them,</l>
            <l>Yet our beſt natures faile in this and vſe them,</l>
            <l>Hee's a rare man that proffer'd, can refuſe them.</l>
            <l>But you great Lord deſcended of a race,</l>
            <l>Which vertue merit, and deſart doth grace,</l>
            <l>Made great by birth and honor, not by chance,</l>
            <l>As <hi>Fortune's</hi> wont her followers to aduance,</l>
            <l>Can better tell theſe things then I can name them,</l>
            <l>And learne, ſuch vaine affections, how to tame them:</l>
            <l>Whereby your Predeceſſors got more grace,</l>
            <l>And more renowne, then time can ere deface:</l>
            <l>Combining to your noble houſe that fame</l>
            <l>Which liues in you vnblemiſht, farre from blame.</l>
            <l>And though that I, great Lord, doe write of that,</l>
            <l>Which Fame, the world, and time haue wondered at,</l>
            <l>And by aduenturing, wrong my ſhallow wit,</l>
            <l>In ayming at the marke I cannot hit.</l>
            <l>Yet let ſome gratious cenſure from your honor</l>
            <l>Fall on my pen, which tooke too much vpon her,</l>
            <l>Since from that ſtreame and fountaine you doe ſpring,</l>
            <l>As this moſt noble lady did, I ſing:</l>
            <l>Her worth impeach't, yours muſt eclypſed bee,</l>
            <l>Which in all things with hers doth co-agree.</l>
            <l>Though my plaine dutie, all too meane, prefers,</l>
            <l>Yet reade great Lord not for my ſake, but hers,</l>
            <l>Which was a light to thoſe, that farre ſucceeds</l>
            <l>For vertuous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and honorable deeds:</l>
            <l>Who drawes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch; how much more then</l>
            <l>Need they, of vertue ſtore to equall them,</l>
            <l>When ſpringing honor in ſuch tender yeares</l>
            <l>Vnto the world, ſo freſh and greene appeares.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:5"/>What ſhall we thinke of after comming time,</l>
            <l>But that your glory more and more will ſhine;</l>
            <l>Where that bright ſtarre, within your breſt begunne,</l>
            <l>May quickly riſe to be a glorious Sunne:</l>
            <l>And in the higheſt Spheare of golden fame,</l>
            <l>Rides heauens large circuite with your noble name,</l>
            <l>So thriue ſtill, honor flouriſh euer faire,</l>
            <l>Let no clouds riſe, ſuch glory to impaire,</l>
            <l>Nor your proceedings any whit diſmay,</l>
            <l>T'eclypſe the beautie of ſo faire a day;</l>
            <l>But that your glaſſe at eu'nings watch match may run</l>
            <l>As faire and cleare, as when it firſt begun.</l>
            <l>Then noble Lord my humble duety ſpare,</l>
            <l>What wants in me, your Honor may repaire,</l>
            <l>And mend thoſe ruinous breaches, which my quill</l>
            <l>Hath fall'n into, for want of better skill:</l>
            <l>And I as bound to this, ſhall tune my ſong,</l>
            <l>Pray heauens true honor may continue long.</l>
            <l>Thus not preſuming, what may be amiſſe,</l>
            <l>I pardon craue, and make an end with this.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:6"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE the Ladie WENTWORTH</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable ere I doe begin</l>
            <l>I pardon craue, preſumption is a ſinne,</l>
            <l>Leſt I too much vpon my ſelfe relying,</l>
            <l>May <hi>Icarus</hi>-like perhaps repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my flying.</l>
            <l>The plague of many Poets, which do think</l>
            <l>Their owne to be the pure immortall drinke,</l>
            <l>But I that farre inferiour am to them,</l>
            <l>Aſcribe no ſuch vain-glory to my pen,</l>
            <l>Nor yet will ouerprize, what I do know</l>
            <l>Is paſt my skill to iudge, or power to ſhow.</l>
            <l>If ought within this little volume lies,</l>
            <l>A worke too weake for your iudicious eyes,</l>
            <l>Which might 'gainſt me the ſmalleſt fire incenſe,</l>
            <l>I ſhould be loath to giue ſo much offence:</l>
            <l>Yet doe not fixe your wrath before you trie,</l>
            <l>And heare great Lady my Apologie.</l>
            <l>Perchance my meanneſſe barres me of that fauour,</l>
            <l>Which others gaine in as vnworthy labour,</l>
            <l>If that it doth or bare originall birth</l>
            <l>In ſight of heauen, is nought or little worth:</l>
            <l>Hee's no accepter of the nobleſt blood,</l>
            <l>Aboue the meaner perſons which are good,</l>
            <l>All's one to him, his power created all,</l>
            <l>Hee's great'ſt with him, that on his name doth call.</l>
            <l>The abiects and the out-caſts of all things,</l>
            <l>In this prerogatiue may compare with Kings:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:6"/>Heauens are not partiall, all's alike reſpected,</l>
            <l>None for their greateſt honor are elected,</l>
            <l>If this be not the cauſe, another yet</l>
            <l>May hazard what this former could not hit,</l>
            <l>And bid me call in queſtion ſtraight my pen,</l>
            <l>That hath not writ ſo learn'd as other men,</l>
            <l>Hauing a ſubiect ſo repleate with honor,</l>
            <l>And could not ſhew no better skill vpon her.</l>
            <l>This plunges deeper, and hard claime doth lay</l>
            <l>Vnto my thoughts, I know not what to ſay:</l>
            <l>But ſince thou can'ſt not paint, nor ſteale no wit</l>
            <l>With borrowed ſhapes, or Artes to furniſh it,</l>
            <l>In plaineſt colours thou haſt truely pen'd them,</l>
            <l>Vertue and honor need no arte to mend them.</l>
            <l>Beſides, it was her pleaſure, minde and will,</l>
            <l>To haue her vertues vnderualued ſtill;</l>
            <l>For it is not ſo true, as common knowne,</l>
            <l>The pureſt vertues neuer ſeeke their owne,</l>
            <l>And heauens agree, and with their names diſpence</l>
            <l>To grace the truth, and leaue out eloquence:</l>
            <l>For he reſpects the heart more then the tongue,</l>
            <l>Or elſe we all ſhould doe his Godhead wrong.</l>
            <l>Then if that heauens in this from blame doth free mee,</l>
            <l>Why ſhould not mortals through his glory ſee mee?</l>
            <l>And ſet mee free from any ſcorne and hate,</l>
            <l>Since heauen in all things, all ſhould imitate.</l>
            <l>It may be yet another may ariſe</l>
            <l>And ſhow it ſelfe vnpleaſing to your eies;</l>
            <l>And that is this: the want of wealth and ſtate,</l>
            <l>Which holds too many in diſgrace and hate,</l>
            <l>Yet in the ſight of heau'ns the poor'ſt are grac'd,</l>
            <l>And are not for their want of meanes diſplac'd:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:7"/>If the ſmall'ſt mite or ſparke of grace he findes</l>
            <l>Doth worke at all, within their hearts and mindes:</l>
            <l>Nor doth he caſt away the pooreſt ſlaue</l>
            <l>From entring in, if grace be found to ſaue;</l>
            <l>But like vnto decayed plants, doth cheriſh</l>
            <l>Their dying roots, and will not let them periſh,</l>
            <l>Then noble Lady, if that theſe may claime</l>
            <l>The leaſt reſpect, and ſhelter me from blame,</l>
            <l>I ſhall be glad: when firſt I vndertooke</l>
            <l>To write to ſuch great minds, this little booke;</l>
            <l>Where my too worthleſſe duetie more affords,</l>
            <l>Conceal'd within, not to be tould in words.</l>
            <l>Accept it (Honor) then ſince 'tis the firſt,</l>
            <l>Your greatneſſe ſoone may grac't, or make it worſe:</l>
            <l>But whether 'tis my fortune or my fate,</l>
            <l>I now muſt take't, repentance comes too late:</l>
            <l>Yet many fauours, farre aboue my merit,</l>
            <l>I haue receiu'd from your moſt noble ſpirit:</l>
            <l>Which makes me hope, that now I ſhall not miſſe,</l>
            <l>But likewiſe be receiu'd and grac'd in this,</l>
            <l>For which Ile ſtudie by my beſt endeauer,</l>
            <l>In faithfull ſeruice, bound faſt yours for euer.</l>
            <l>Then, noble Ladie, deigne to take a view</l>
            <l>Of thoſe faire vertuous parts, and honors true,</l>
            <l>Which faire example left ſo rich behinde,</l>
            <l>To fill the vertuous ſtorehouſe of your minde,</l>
            <l>Whoſe worthie branches from that tree deſcended</l>
            <l>Make honors goe with vertues rich attended:</l>
            <l>Where ſome of them, if all you doe not finde,</l>
            <l>Ingrauen in your honorable minde.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:7"/>
            <head>TO SIR HENRY CROFTS.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F that my lines may be at all reſpected,</l>
            <l>And not for their vnworthineſſe reiected,</l>
            <l>Which, though too meane, faine would remember yet</l>
            <l>The loue I owe, which many doe forget,</l>
            <l>The ſeruice and the dutie which deſires,</l>
            <l>(Though your deſarts farre greater worth requires)</l>
            <l>To yeeld ſome thankes by meane endeauors preſt,</l>
            <l>You in your better iudgement know the reſt:</l>
            <l>From Shepheards cells, expect no more to finde,</l>
            <l>Then what may pleaſe the beſt contented minde.</l>
            <l>Our tables are not furniſht with ſuch coſt</l>
            <l>For ſumptuous cheere, or lofty faire to boaſt:</l>
            <l>Such as we haue we giue, on truſt we goe not,</l>
            <l>To entertaine you, Sir, with that we owe not:</l>
            <l>Nor yet by ſtealth doe ſeeke to winne your loue,</l>
            <l>To beare the name of that we cannot proue:</l>
            <l>Though intertainment, houſe and cheere be ſmall,</l>
            <l>The heart is true which doth inuite you all;</l>
            <l>And will in better wiſhes more content yee,</l>
            <l>Then in this booke my barraine braine hath lent yee.</l>
            <l>I cannot fly in learned loftie phraſes,</l>
            <l>But doe adorne my ſtile with truth, not praiſes:</l>
            <l>Nor paſſe I for conceits, which are preciſe,</l>
            <l>But only write to pleaſe the vertuous wiſe:</l>
            <l>For I haue read, that true and noble mindes,</l>
            <l>The beſt content in willing natures findes.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:8"/>Honor receiues no fall, by want of skill</l>
            <l>If Gentle doome doe fall vpon my quill:</l>
            <l>Then, worthy Knight, ſince that you are ſome ayme,</l>
            <l>And not the leaſt hopes that my Muſe doth clayme,</l>
            <l>Accept and pardon what amiſſe is found,</l>
            <l>That built this frame vpon ſo weake a ground;</l>
            <l>Nor let not duety, wanting learned lore,</l>
            <l>Be counted folly, nor my ſeruice poore;</l>
            <l>But be receiued, wherein it comes farre ſhort,</l>
            <l>Reſpecting more my will, then my deſart.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:8"/>
            <head>TO THE LADIE CROMPTON.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, 'tis not for want of time but wit,</l>
            <l>That I no ſooner of her vertues writ;</l>
            <l>Though late, yet take that chance which doth befall,</l>
            <l>Better thus meanly ſung, then not at all.</l>
            <l>Where I delaying for ſome learned wit,</l>
            <l>Let ſlipt occaſion which might better fit:</l>
            <l>Yet ſince her vertues were ſo great and many,</l>
            <l>Which cannot iuſtly be denide of any;</l>
            <l>Much leſſe of you, and of that houſe before,</l>
            <l>Where they ingrauen lie twice ten times more,</l>
            <l>Such kinde affections worke in worthy breſts,</l>
            <l>That honor dying, yet is not deceaſt;</l>
            <l>But liues in you, where often it doth finde</l>
            <l>A heauie <hi>memorandum</hi> from the minde:</l>
            <l>Such honored friends are not ſo ſoone forgotten,</l>
            <l>Though in their graues they long lie dead and rotten,</l>
            <l>But euer now and then the Spirit will moue,</l>
            <l>And fetch a ſigh or two for her it loues,</l>
            <l>Bewraying of it ſelfe in teares, when any</l>
            <l>Speakes of the name of noble Lady <hi>Cheany:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then faire and worthy Lady, whoſe pure minde</l>
            <l>Doth vertue in ſo faire a manſion binde,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:9"/>Whoſe parts for naturall, morall, and diuine,</l>
            <l>Excels the force of my weake feeble rime.</l>
            <l>Vouchſafe to reade her, whom you once ſo lou'd,</l>
            <l>And ſpare thoſe faults which loue and duetie mou'd;</l>
            <l>Nor, Madam, doe not iudge my ſeruice ſlack,</l>
            <l>That payes not heere your merits what they lack,</l>
            <l>Nor priſe your worth, nor that faire marke can hit,</l>
            <l>But make affection play the theefe for it,</l>
            <l>Where ſince I reacht at wit, as 'twere by ſtealth,</l>
            <l>Let that worth in you better praiſe your ſelfe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:9"/>
            <head>TO THE LADIE BENNET.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, the ſeruice I doe owe to all</l>
            <l>Your ſiſters, and your houſe in generall,</l>
            <l>Would ask a volume, if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I could write it,</l>
            <l>Or had but wit ſufficient to indite it.</l>
            <l>Yet, Madam, ſince I haue no worldly ſtore,</l>
            <l>I giue you that, I neuer gaue before:</l>
            <l>And wanting one, yet may you take the other,</l>
            <l>The fruits, my weake inuention could diſcouer.</l>
            <l>Heere in this little volume may be read,</l>
            <l>Some of her noble vertues, being dead;</l>
            <l>Where you may ſtriue in imitation,</l>
            <l>To make more glorious by your application.</l>
            <l>Some can gleane vertue from the ſmalleſt things,</l>
            <l>And hony ſucke from meaneſt flowers that ſprings:</l>
            <l>Then how much more from her, whoſe honor true,</l>
            <l>Such ſtore of vertues doth afford to you.</l>
            <l>Where, Madam, your faire intellectiue minde,</l>
            <l>May more then I can, or haue vttered, finde.</l>
            <l>Reade o're her life, and in your iudgement view her,</l>
            <l>Who hath not much admir'd, that euer knew her?</l>
            <l>Where eyes, eares, hearts, are vaniſhed with the ſame,</l>
            <l>Of her long happie, and time-honored name.</l>
            <l>Then, Madam, ſince my meanneſſe is too great,</l>
            <l>Of ſuch a waightie ſubiect to intreat:</l>
            <l>Some fauour lend, to grace this worke the better,</l>
            <l>For which acceptance, I will die your debter.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:10"/>
            <head>TO THE LADIE MILDMAY.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, ſome ſtrangeneſſe may poſſeſſe you, when</l>
            <l>You looke on theſe, and thinke vpon my pen,</l>
            <l>What vaine and high conceit my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome haunted,</l>
            <l>That would not be with ſuch great honor daunted.</l>
            <l>Yet, kinde and vertuous Lady, let me craue</l>
            <l>What others in the like attempts may haue:</l>
            <l>You which doe repreſent to me her name,</l>
            <l>How can I hold you guiltleſſe of her fame?</l>
            <l>But they muſt both concurre within your breaſt,</l>
            <l>To keepe for euer their moſt bounteous feaſt:</l>
            <l>No ſmall affection ſhee could beare to you,</l>
            <l>Giue Honor and your owne Deſarts their due:</l>
            <l>Shee lou'd you liuing, and with many graces</l>
            <l>Did fill your ſoule, which vertue now imbraces:</l>
            <l>VVhere Nature hath ſo well the workeman plai'd,</l>
            <l>And her full due to euery member pai'd;</l>
            <l>That nought doth want within her bounteous ſtore,</l>
            <l>But lent it you to grace her glorie more.</l>
            <l>Then, faire and worthie Ladie, condeſcend</l>
            <l>To reade theſe humble lines, and fauour lend</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:10"/>To what may with your iudgement diſagree,</l>
            <l>Your liking lent, can grace both it and mee:</l>
            <l>For ſuch rare mindes with noble deeds inſue,</l>
            <l>VVill aske no little wit to ſing them true:</l>
            <l>'Tis no ſmall worke, nor ſleight, nor eaſie taske,</l>
            <l>VVherein her vertues doe ſo dimly maske.</l>
            <l>VVhat my defectiue pen doth want of skill.</l>
            <l>Your vertuous minde accepting, may fulfill.</l>
            <l>To whoſe cleare boſome I doe leaue the reſt,</l>
            <l>VVhich owes you more, then can be heere expreſt.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:11"/>
            <head>TO THE IMPARTIALL AND indifferent Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REader whatſoeuer thou art accept, if may be,</l>
               <l>Theſe humble verſes clad in ſhepheards weeds,</l>
               <l>My ſubiect is an honourable Lady,</l>
               <l>And of her vertuous life and ſacred deeds.</l>
               <l>Therefore I would intreat thee when thou reads</l>
               <l>Vomit no venome forth, nor poyſoned gall,</l>
               <l>Leſt that the like vpon thy pen befall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Perchance thou lookst for, that I cannot giue,</l>
               <l>Some ouer-flowing phraſe of eloquence,</l>
               <l>Wherein her high deſerts might better liue,</l>
               <l>And yeeld the curious artiſt leſſe offence:</l>
               <l>But with his itching vaine I can diſpenſe</l>
               <l>And tell him this, pure vertue loues to weare</l>
               <l>Not all rich ſtuffe, but ſometimes Camels haire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I doe not know thy nature nor condition,</l>
               <l>Be what thou wilt Ile nere orerunne thy fauour,</l>
               <l>I onely write to gentle diſpoſitions</l>
               <l>And may as well reſpect the meaneſt labour</l>
               <l>Then doe not ſhew thy ſelfe of rough behauiour</l>
               <l>As ſharply for to cenſure what is written,</l>
               <l>Mad dogges they are when none can ſcape vnbitten.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then paſſe thy verdit gently on my lines,</l>
               <l>Shew not thy ſelfe more cruell then the reſt,</l>
               <l>I write not for to pleaſe diſordered times,</l>
               <l>But thoſe to whom time hath mark'd for the beſt,</l>
               <l>Then take thy courſe or yeeld to my requeſt,</l>
               <l>For I do ſtand indifferent rightly then</l>
               <l>Speake what thou wilt ſpeake and blame not my pen.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:11"/>
            <head>VERTVES ANATOMY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ee powers diuine, ſole aide of humane wits,</l>
               <l>Aſſiſt me with your ſacred ſpirit a while,</l>
               <l>And guide me in that path where vertue ſits,</l>
               <l>And not with idle matters to defile</l>
               <l>My time, her honour, and thy glory beſt,</l>
               <l>With light vaine pamphlets, as haue done the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But in ſome fairer courſe direct my lines,</l>
               <l>That they may quiet paſſe vntoucht of wrongs,</l>
               <l>Too weake I knowe to pleaſe theſe curious times,</l>
               <l>VVhich ſwarmes about like bees with ſtinging to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues:</l>
               <l>Kepe thy ſteps euen, for there is none to right thee,</l>
               <l>If once <hi>Detraction</hi> that mad dog doth bite thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then Oh thou dolefull Dame and tragick muſe,</l>
               <l>VVhich in blacke ſable tunes doſt euer mourne:</l>
               <l>Some of thy power into my breſt infuſe,</l>
               <l>That my dim candle may the better burne,</l>
               <l>And giue the clearer light vnto her honour:</l>
               <l>Admird ſo much of all that e're heard on her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:12"/>
               <l>A ſubiect far vnfit for ſuch a quill</l>
               <l>But that I thinke ſome fatall hand doth guide it,</l>
               <l>And carries mee away againſt my will,</l>
               <l>Not ſuffering me within my breaſt to hide it:</l>
               <l>Such fire as this doth ſeldome burne within me</l>
               <l>That hath ſuch power thus from my ſelfe to win me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor doe I thinke ſufficient my weake skill</l>
               <l>So great a ſubiect for to entertaine,</l>
               <l>Far be ſuch thoughts from my vnworthy quill</l>
               <l>VVhich humbly writes, and not for glory vaine:</l>
               <l>No I doe know my ſelfe, praiſe cannot tempt me,</l>
               <l>Since Learning, wit, and all things elſe preuent me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for ſome ſtricter bond, which neerer ties me,</l>
               <l>And zeale vnto that honord houſe I owe,</l>
               <l>VVhich far aboue my power doth ſeeke to trie me,</l>
               <l>My duty in theſe humble lines to ſhew:</l>
               <l>This mite of wit, this little tallent lent me,</l>
               <l>Which my bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſeruice, al too meane hath ſent thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For which I doe confeſſe <hi>Minerua</hi> might</l>
               <l>Haue cauſe to ſing in memorable lines,</l>
               <l>The Muſes, if they did her honor right,</l>
               <l>Might haue ſufficient worke for after times;</l>
               <l>And all the learned wits that were of yore,</l>
               <l>Might ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome paines to grace her vertues more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this vilde age which for the moſt part graces</l>
               <l>The vitious nature and the hartleſſe mindes:</l>
               <l>And honors aſſes ſpring from golden races</l>
               <l>VVherein true merit ſeldome any findes:</l>
               <l>For where there's one ſuch, fit for honors place,</l>
               <l>Thers ten for him which fils them with diſgrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:12"/>
               <l>For gilded greatneſſe ſticke too much with prayſes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſwelling pride bears al things down before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
               <l>This age to greater fame and fortune rayſes,</l>
               <l>That like to Demigods the world adores them,</l>
               <l>What pearles of prayſes daily of them rings,</l>
               <l>Blowne with the winde of adulations wings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What armes, what trophies haue they not erected,</l>
               <l>What glory brought their vpſtart houſes to,</l>
               <l>And in this world what perſons more reſpected</l>
               <l>VVhat iſ't ſo hard but that their power can doe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mamon</hi> their God, can purchaſe all for them</l>
               <l>Lands, fame, renowne, nay more the ſoules of men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe like the Dragon carry with their tayle</l>
               <l>The third part of the ſtarres, and rule the earth:</l>
               <l>Their pride and power with controule preuaile,</l>
               <l>And eate vp poore men like a timeleſſe dearth:</l>
               <l>Theſe which their greatneſſe keepe the world in awe;</l>
               <l>Their will, their reaſon, and muſt ſtand for lawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For which great cauſe Dame vertue euer mourns</l>
               <l>That her owne heires are deſtitute of fauours,</l>
               <l>And others worthleſſe placed in their romes</l>
               <l>To feed vpon their true deſeruing labors:</l>
               <l>VVhilſt they doe ſwell with honours ſhe doth pine,</l>
               <l>And muſt be forc'd to beg or ſerue the time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh yee deſired times reuerſe your courſe</l>
               <l>Vnto thoſe antient cuſtomes which were then,</l>
               <l>And let not theſe preferments lighs of worſe</l>
               <l>VVhich were ordain'd for wiſe and learned men,</l>
               <l>For honor, vertue, wiſedome, worth and merit,</l>
               <l>Are the true heires thoſe places to inherit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:13"/>
               <l>Oh pardon me if I miſtake my pen,</l>
               <l>And from my purpoſe doe a little ſwarue,</l>
               <l>It is the great abuſes of theſe men,</l>
               <l>Which doe the time, themſelues and fortune ſerue,</l>
               <l>That are vnto that height of greatneſſe growne,</l>
               <l>Masking in merits ſhape, and not their owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Was this the firſt cauſe of gentilitie,</l>
               <l>Or from what ſtocke or roote did it deſcend</l>
               <l>Was this the ground of true humanitie,</l>
               <l>Their greatnes, by their greatnes to offend:</l>
               <l>Was this the race from whom all Gentles ſprung</l>
               <l>Wherein that worthy name was firſt begun?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Was lands or large poſſeſſions the foundation</l>
               <l>That men vnto that reuerend title came,</l>
               <l>Or this worlds largeſt rule or domination,</l>
               <l>Whereon ſo many did their glories frame,</l>
               <l>If theſe muſt be the cauſe what will you call</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> to be, which firſt poſſeſſed all?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If what this earths great compaſſe forth could bring</l>
               <l>Whereof the leaſt part makes a Gentile now:</l>
               <l>Might neither be a Gentlle, Lord, nor King</l>
               <l>Nor to him honors nor renowne allowe,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould his broode with pride ſo much abound,</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſing but a little peece of ground?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Waſt wealth or all the riches of the earth,</l>
               <l>Without the which the beſt are held in ſcorne,</l>
               <l>That could compoſe a Gentleman by birth,</l>
               <l>Being meerely from the loynes of <hi>Adam</hi> borne?</l>
               <l>Oh no if I ſhould craue that faire diſcent,</l>
               <l>From that foule roote I feare I ſhould be ſhent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:13"/>
               <l>Waſt might or ſome oppreſſing <hi>Nymrods</hi> hand</l>
               <l>Whoſe powerfull pride did awe the weaker creatures,</l>
               <l>And ſought by force and violence to command</l>
               <l>More then his owne, and raiſe that name to nature,</l>
               <l>No heau'ns forbid vſurping tyranny,</l>
               <l>Should ere be ſprung from true gentility.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What was it then from humaine birth deriu'd</l>
               <l>And had it her firſt being from that kinde,</l>
               <l>The marke for which antiquitie long hath ſtriu'd,</l>
               <l>And which doth challeng the moſt faireſt ſigne?</l>
               <l>Oh, how can nature (I would aske this firſt)</l>
               <l>Be gentle cald, whom heauens before had curſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No <hi>Adam,</hi> if that theſe can title claime,</l>
               <l>(As none without them now liues in requeſt)</l>
               <l>And challeng to themſelues this gentle name,</l>
               <l>Which at the firſt was onely giuen the beſt:</l>
               <l>Then was thy birth, thy wealth, and worldly ſtore</l>
               <l>The moſt, and great'ſt: what man had euer more?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, theſe are but th'admired broode of time,</l>
               <l>Blowne like a bladder vp with froth and winde,</l>
               <l>Made worldly great by prouidence diuine</l>
               <l>When ſmall gentility reſteth in their minde:</l>
               <l>Their fortunes riſes but their vertues fall,</l>
               <l>Poor'ſt in greatſt plenty, weake when great'ſt of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But why doe I to little purpoſe ſtriue,</l>
               <l>And make my ſelfe more curious far then wiſe,</l>
               <l>This name from her beginning to deriue?</l>
               <l>When euery vulgar worldling (too preciſe)</l>
               <l>Doe hold too little for his ſwelling pride,</l>
               <l>Whom no bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds hold, nor compaſſe true can guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:14"/>
               <l>Yet ſince my laboring pen ſo much doth craue,</l>
               <l>To ſearch the ground of this ſo worthy name,</l>
               <l>I muſt attempt with that bare skill I haue</l>
               <l>For to define, leaſt that I purchaſe blame.</l>
               <l>For all theſe foure rehearſt can neuer doe it,</l>
               <l>Although they lay hard claime, and title to it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Twas vertue, merit, and an humble minde;</l>
               <l>'Twas curteous qualities, and moſt faire conditions;</l>
               <l>'Twas true deſart, loue, and affections kinde,</l>
               <l>Grac't with the mil'dſt and pureſt diſpoſitions;</l>
               <l>'Twas learned arts, and honor which proceeds,</l>
               <l>Not from rough might, but weake &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teous deeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Twas an aſſiſting, not oppreſſing hand,</l>
               <l>That did extend to charitable vſes,</l>
               <l>Defending right, and truth which could not ſtand</l>
               <l>Free in thoſe daies from wrongs, and ſome abuſes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe zeale did burne with vertue, and made all</l>
               <l>Their end true honor, not an others fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'T was iuſtice, piety, and a ſacred ſpirit,</l>
               <l>Which firſt inforc'd that faire name to be giuen,</l>
               <l>Ador'd with famous deeeds, and noble merits</l>
               <l>Whoſe birth, and being is deriu'd from heauen;</l>
               <l>No carnall birth no wealth, nor worldly honor</l>
               <l>Can well be ſaid to haue affinite from her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet the moſt (this age ſo much bewitches)</l>
               <l>Digreſſe from theſe, or elſe my muſe muſtly</l>
               <l>Tranſlated now to honor, ſtate, and riches,</l>
               <l>In which moſt hold, is tru'ſt gentility,</l>
               <l>But let them haue it, I will not contend,</l>
               <l>Their honors may deceiue them all i'th end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:14"/>
               <l>Great King of heauen and earth, how ſhall I ſpeake,</l>
               <l>Which am but duſt, and aſhes vnto thee,</l>
               <l>When my ſoules faculties are all too weake</l>
               <l>Once to conceiue the meaneſt thought of thee?</l>
               <l>And yet thou tearmſt thy ſelfe but Sonne of man</l>
               <l>Which vild wormes ſcorne, whoſe glorie's but a ſpan.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ambitions age, can Auarice blinde thee ſo,</l>
               <l>To build ſuch caſtles in vncertaine ayre?</l>
               <l>What can your honors, powers and riches doe?</l>
               <l>For age, and death thei'le leaue you to deſpaire,</l>
               <l>Where thou canſt not redeeme an howers time,</l>
               <l>Though al the goods in thouſand worlds were thine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke yee to buy his fauour with a price,</l>
               <l>Or fee him with ſo many golden mines?</l>
               <l>Can any let ſinne purchaſe paradiſe,</l>
               <l>Or giue ſufficient ranſome for your crimes?</l>
               <l>Oh no theſe dreames doe but your ſenſes tickle,</l>
               <l>For in that hower, all that you hau's too little.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reuerſe your error, let not theſe moleſt you,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould faire falſhood blinde your mentall eies?</l>
               <l>That it may once be ſaid vertue poſſeſt you,</l>
               <l>Wherein the trueſt fame and honor lies:</l>
               <l>For ſmal's that greatnes, poore &amp; weak's that glory,</l>
               <l>Which hath his truſt vppon things tranſitory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſeeke not to enrich poſterity,</l>
               <l>With an oppreſſing hand and cruell might:</l>
               <l>Nor build your houſes vp by tyranny,</l>
               <l>Nor take poſſeſſion of the poore mans right:</l>
               <l>Leſt <hi>Achab</hi>-like, in buying ſo you ſell</l>
               <l>Your houſe, your ſoule, and all you haue to hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:15"/>
               <l>VVhat profit ſhall your tired ſoules receiue</l>
               <l>Of all theſe riches, you haue heap'd together?</l>
               <l>VVhen in a moment you muſt take your leaue</l>
               <l>Of all your ſtore, and goe you know not whither:</l>
               <l>Your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew your wealth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world your ſhame,</l>
               <l>And all doe hate the memory of your name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt odious euer, hated of God and men,</l>
               <l>Accurſed riches, which will waſte in vſing,</l>
               <l>Vnluckie, and vnbleſſed iſſue then,</l>
               <l>VVhen all you haue is purchas'd by abuſing:</l>
               <l>Your parents knew not that their goods ill gotten</l>
               <l>Their heires wold ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were dead &amp; rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh what a ioyfull thing 'tis to behold,</l>
               <l>Heires to ſucceed their fires in vertuous lore?</l>
               <l>And ſtriue their houſes honor to vphold</l>
               <l>VVith greater glory then it had before:</l>
               <l>Studying by noble deeds t'inrich their name,</l>
               <l>To their immortall praiſe and endleſſe fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ah I feare, what I would not miſtruſt,</l>
               <l>That heires to prodigall vices rather turne;</l>
               <l>And leaue their honors trodden in the duſt,</l>
               <l>The loſſe whereof ſome ancient houſes mourne,</l>
               <l>Not liuing like themſelues, in birth; but ſlaues,</l>
               <l>Burying all vertue in their fathers graues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The cauſe of which great waſte and fall of heires,</l>
               <l>I iudge the impious times of wretched fathers;</l>
               <l>VVhoſe auaritious thoughts and greedie cares;</l>
               <l>To fatten them and theirs, vniuſtly gathers;</l>
               <l>And waſte their braines in ſtudying day and night,</l>
               <l>To purchaſe that, which is anothers right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:15"/>
               <l>Oh why ſhould theſe be grac'd? why ſhould a pen</l>
               <l>Dip'd in the pureſt liquor of thoſe ſprings,</l>
               <l>Attend the earthly glory of theſe men,</l>
               <l>VVhich ſhame vnto the trueſt honor brings:</l>
               <l>As we doe ſee Fame none ſo much doth boaſt</l>
               <l>As thoſe whoſe liues haue tyranniz'd it moſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If theſe, vnto ſuch fortunes haue attain'd,</l>
               <l>Built on the ſlippery ground of fading Fame,</l>
               <l>Then what great glorie ſhall thy honor gaine?</l>
               <l>Or what ſufficient pen can praiſe the ſame?</l>
               <l>If Vice with Tombes, and Epitaphes is renown'd,</l>
               <l>VVherwith ſhal thy rare vertuous deeds be crown'd?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If out-ſide honor, if vſurped greatneſſe,</l>
               <l>If painted pictures of Iniquitie,</l>
               <l>Can haue their praiſes ſung with wondrous ſweetneſſe,</l>
               <l>Which nere deſeru'd the meaneſt dignitie;</l>
               <l>VVhat ſhall the true bred honor of the minde,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with vertues excellencies, finde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Did not thy ventures challenge from Fames wings,</l>
               <l>One quill or pen t'immortalize thy name?</l>
               <l>Is any enuious Serpent left that ſtings,</l>
               <l>Or can with th'ſmalleſt tincture touch thy fame?</l>
               <l>Are not thy vertues and thy honors bleſt</l>
               <l>VVith as great grace, and glory as the reſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then why ſhould not ſome worthy ſpirits vpriſe,</l>
               <l>And with vndaunted quill her honor ſing?</l>
               <l>VVhy ſhould they not her worth and vertues priſe,</l>
               <l>As high as theirs which from corruption ſprings?</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſhame's their glory, &amp; their aime's (their ſtain)</l>
               <l>At nought but worldly things, and glory vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:16"/>
               <l>No, worthy Lady, doe not thinke a Tombe</l>
               <l>Can thy freſh memory from this world diuide:</l>
               <l>Nor thinke that this earths all-deuouring wombe</l>
               <l>Within her bowels, can thy vertues hide,</l>
               <l>Nor wrong thy merits, nor arreſt thy worth,</l>
               <l>Which ſpite of Time, will ſpring and flouriſh forth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That monumentall white, faire marble Tombe,</l>
               <l>Cannot containe thy noble deeds and merits,</l>
               <l>When all the world is knowne too little roome</l>
               <l>To comprehend, in bounds, thy boundleſſe ſpirit:</l>
               <l>But ſtill ſhall time, with vs, be euer telling</l>
               <l>Ages to come, thy vertuous life excelling.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor, doe not thinke, though in corruptions bed</l>
               <l>Thy body lies interr'd at Tuddington,</l>
               <l>That therefore thou art quite forgot and dead,</l>
               <l>Or from our memories cleane exil'd and gone:</l>
               <l>No, no, thy name and fame againe will raiſe thee,</l>
               <l>And ſpite of death, will make the world to praiſe thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No 'twas decreed of euerlaſting fate,</l>
               <l>That vertue ſhould endure, and neuer die:</l>
               <l>Made to out-liue Times rage, and longeſt date,</l>
               <l>Writ with a pen of ſure eternitie:</l>
               <l>Where if the Muſes faile her worth to raiſe,</l>
               <l>Then babes and ſucklings will ſpeak forth her praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which hath induc'd my infant Muſe to write,</l>
               <l>My ſuckling wits, which all too meane preſumes,</l>
               <l>Where if that learning cannot well indite,</l>
               <l>How ſhall I doe with theſe impoliſh'd tunes?</l>
               <l>But hope the beſt; for euils come ſooneſt then,</l>
               <l>When leaſt ſuſpected, and deſeruing them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:16"/>
               <l>Then launch into the Ocean of her honor,</l>
               <l>So rare a Phaenix, and our countries wonder:</l>
               <l>Thy Muſe, I doubt much merit will take from her;</l>
               <l>Or elſe her ſilly backe will ſplit aſunder,</l>
               <l>Yet beare the ſayles vp, heauens may ſend a winde</l>
               <l>T'inſpire me how to praiſe her vertuous minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which they that true religion pure and bleſt,</l>
               <l>Not mixed with Idolatrie, nor defil'd:</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertuous life and deeds did her profeſſe,</l>
               <l>An Iſraelite true, in whom there was no guile;</l>
               <l>Imbracing of the ſacred truth in loue,</l>
               <l>From which no worldly cares could her remoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſought to know and learne thoſe artes Diuine.</l>
               <l>Which onely vnto true ſaluation tend;</l>
               <l>And therein much did exerciſe her minde,</l>
               <l>To profit by the truth which all defend:</l>
               <l>Miſplacing errors, which doe ſeeke to blinde</l>
               <l>The way of truth, in ſelfe-affected minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No verball, but a mentall true profeſſion,</l>
               <l>Ingrauen in her honorable breſt;</l>
               <l>Wherein it tooke moſt ſure and deepe impreſſion,</l>
               <l>That grace and honor heere did euer reſt:</l>
               <l>Making the one illuſtrious by the other,</l>
               <l>As if they were both twins, ſprung from one mother.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſurely ſo they are, as neere allyed,</l>
               <l>Who wins their honors by their vertues firſt</l>
               <l>Can witneſſe well their noble deeds haue tried,</l>
               <l>Though Fortune now beſtowes them on the worſt:</l>
               <l>'Tis but externall honor they doe winne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe houſes end, before they doe beginne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:17"/>
               <l>For thou Religion art a ſeely ſound,</l>
               <l>Accounted in theſe nice and curious times,</l>
               <l>Of many mightie troubles made the ground,</l>
               <l>VVhom ouer-ſearching doubts, and errors blindes:</l>
               <l>So many truths, that which of them to take,</l>
               <l>To many wandering wits doe queſtion make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is the truth, they'le neuer ſtart away;</l>
               <l>From this vnto another ſtraight they are gone:</l>
               <l>Then to that ſect they know not what to ſay,</l>
               <l>Thus are they buſie in all, but firme in none:</l>
               <l>Then this they like, then that, then ſtraight theyle turne</l>
               <l>To any thing, I thinke, before theyle burne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such trees, which like the fig-tree ſeemes moſt faire,</l>
               <l>VVhen nought but leaues and bloſſomes it affords;</l>
               <l>And in the eyes of th'world are iudg'd moſt rare,</l>
               <l>That onely paints Religion out in words,</l>
               <l>That learnes to tip their tongues with Artes diuine,</l>
               <l>VVhen damn'd Hypocriſie reſteth in their minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhoſe geſture, workes, lookes, words, and actions all</l>
               <l>VVith ſimilar ſhowes are varniſh'd to deceiue men,</l>
               <l>VVith heau p vp hands and eyes to heauen they call,</l>
               <l>As if deuotion would of ſenſe bereaue them:</l>
               <l>And knock their breſts, when as their hearts within</l>
               <l>Lie buried vp in fleſh, and bloud, and ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such ſtrange comixtures of Religion holds them,</l>
               <l>That they, like mad-men, care not where they bite:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iudas</hi>-like, a little price hath ſold them,</l>
               <l>That euen the worſt of errors they doe like:</l>
               <l>Thus are they, through their owne raſh-daring skill,</l>
               <l>Led captiue of the Diuell, to doe his will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:17"/>
               <l>How many ſtrange Religions are there found,</l>
               <l>That will diſpute of truth, and ſeeme to know it?</l>
               <l>How many ſects, and rules, yet all vnſound?</l>
               <l>As this vaine, light-beleeuing age can ſhow it.</l>
               <l>If ſuch a number into errors fall,</l>
               <l>How many more, which hold no truth at all?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good God, which art the onely truth and guide,</l>
               <l>Keep's from thoſe errors, wherein ſome are caught,</l>
               <l>That we from thee may neuer fall nor ſlide,</l>
               <l>But willingly embrace the Goſpell taught:</l>
               <l>That no inuentions, hereſies, crafts or guiles</l>
               <l>May worke in vs, our ſafetie to beguile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, worthy Lady, who did'ſt keepe the truth</l>
               <l>From ſuperſtition, and Idolatrie free;</l>
               <l>Both in old age, in middle yeares and youth,</l>
               <l>That in ſuch greatneſſe few haue done like thee:</l>
               <l>Where many liue, to whom that name belongs,</l>
               <l>Which onely Chriſtianize it in their tongues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thy firme reſolution fixed was,</l>
               <l>And vnremoued ſtood againſt all thoſe,</l>
               <l>Which ſeemes to ſet a colour, and a gloſſe</l>
               <l>Vpon Religion, falſhood to incloſe:</l>
               <l>Vnder which faire pretext often doth lie,</l>
               <l>Moſt dangerous deepe deceits our ſoules to trie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The truth thy ſoule delighted: not to ſtriue</l>
               <l>On idle queſtions, which no profit brings;</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt ſome new ſought inuentions can contriue,</l>
               <l>To draw hard queſtions from the meaneſt things:</l>
               <l>Wreſting thoſe words, that ſence, to what they'd haue it,</l>
               <l>And not as right and true conſtructions craue it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:18"/>
               <l>But thou, the praiſe of theſe vnconſtant times,</l>
               <l>Mad'ſt not this world the patterne to doe ill;</l>
               <l>But like a candle did'ſt in darkneſſe ſhine,</l>
               <l>And fram'dſt thy life vnto thy Makers will,</l>
               <l>Not toſſed to and fro with euery winde,</l>
               <l>Which wraps in many errors wandring mindes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But did'ſt continue, to thy vtmoſt breath,</l>
               <l>A zealous Proteſtant, and religious friend:</l>
               <l>Not ſtain'd with hereſie in thy life, nor death,</l>
               <l>But ſeald'ſt thy laſt gaſpe with a glorious end:</l>
               <l>Which made the Angels ſing, and heauens reioyce,</l>
               <l>That thou with <hi>Mary</hi> madeſt ſo good a choyſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy faith as great and rare, did apprehend</l>
               <l>The ſecond perſon in the Trinitie:</l>
               <l>On whom thy whole ſaluation did depend,</l>
               <l>Wrought by his paſſions ſo effectually:</l>
               <l>Not mingling of his merits with humane powers,</l>
               <l>Aſcribing that to vs, which is not ours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to thy ſelfe by priuate application,</l>
               <l>Did'ſt ceize on all thoſe promiſes ſweet and faire,</l>
               <l>Writ in the Scriptures for our conſolation,</l>
               <l>To keepe vs vp from horror and deſpaire:</l>
               <l>That when deepe flouds, &amp; waters ſeeme to drowne vs,</l>
               <l>Our faith may ſhine in darkneſſe then, &amp; crowne vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And bring our ſoules into that glorious reſt,</l>
               <l>Wrought by his paſſions, ſufferings, death and merit,</l>
               <l>Which he hath purchas'd for the choſen beſt,</l>
               <l>After this mortall labour to inherit:</l>
               <l>Redeeming vs, when we were caſt away,</l>
               <l>With ſuch a price as none but he could pay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:18"/>
               <l>That holy one, that pure vnſpotted Lambe,</l>
               <l>That did deſcend, from his eternall throwne,</l>
               <l>For vs vile ſinners, being God and man;</l>
               <l>To ſatisfie the wrath of heauen alone:</l>
               <l>And vnderwent ſuch torments, griefes, and paines,</l>
               <l>To make his greateſt loſſe, our greateſt gaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh happie Lady, whoſe erected minde,</l>
               <l>This glorious obiect of thy faith ſo loues?</l>
               <l>Thy ſoules delight, which ioyes and comforts finde,</l>
               <l>Where all the triall of thy faith he proues:</l>
               <l>And viewes the pure deuotions of thy heart,</l>
               <l>Which for his ſeruice thou had'ſt ſet apart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There, in that euerlaſting booke of fate,</l>
               <l>Are written downe the triall of thy loue,</l>
               <l>Thy faith, zeale, piety, and that happy ſtate,</l>
               <l>Which far beyond our thoughts, thy ſoule doth proue:</l>
               <l>Such great felicitie, ioyes, which ioyes excell,</l>
               <l>That tongues of men and Angels cannot tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Could the heau'ns ſee thy labours and endeuor,</l>
               <l>And to thy louing cares giue no regard?</l>
               <l>Thy conſtancie, whereby thou did'ſt perſeuer</l>
               <l>Vnto the end, and yeeld thee no reward?</l>
               <l>Oh no, 'tis hard to thinke, but worſe to ſay,</l>
               <l>That heau'ns great giuer ſhould himſelfe denay!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that rewards vniuſt and wicked men</l>
               <l>With ample benefits, ſhall he not be kinde</l>
               <l>Vnto his owne deare choſen children then;</l>
               <l>Or ſuffer them to ſlip out of his minde?</l>
               <l>If he ſo liberall be to the vniuſt,</l>
               <l>What ſhall he be to thoſe that in him truſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:19"/>
               <l>Oh no, Great Lady, he will doe no wrong,</l>
               <l>Nor once deny himſelfe, let none ſo thinke;</l>
               <l>Hee's iuſt and true, although he beareth long;</l>
               <l>Nor is he blinde, although he ſeeme to winke:</l>
               <l>But doth behold thy faith, which neuer faints,</l>
               <l>Where he doth crowne thee with his deareſt Saints.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That bitter combate held with fleſh and blood,</l>
               <l>And mightie conflict, which aſſaults the beſt;</l>
               <l>Which by his powerfull hand thou haſt withſtood,</l>
               <l>And quench'd thoſe fiery darts which neuer reſt:</l>
               <l>But ſtill new battailes, warre and ſtrife begin</l>
               <l>Againſt our ſoules, faire Sions fort to win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet all theſe cannot ſhake thy glorious hold,</l>
               <l>See firme and conſtant faith doth ſtill endure,</l>
               <l>Which makes thy truſt and confidence ſo bold;</l>
               <l>Ayde him that moſt vndoubted ayde aſſure;</l>
               <l>He takes thy part, he will not ſee thee foil'd,</l>
               <l>Nor to thy foes become a prey, nor ſpoild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heere did the triall of thy faith appeare,</l>
               <l>In his continuall fight with fleſh and blood,</l>
               <l>Which ſhew'd thy loue vnto thy Sauiour deare,</l>
               <l>Which could not be by worldly hopes withſtood:</l>
               <l>But ſtill perſiſted, ſtriuing for to winne</l>
               <l>That powerfull monſter, <hi>Hydra</hi>-headed ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou neuer vnto Saints and Angels prayde,</l>
               <l>Nor mad'ſt petitions to them in thy need;</l>
               <l>Which whil'ſt they liu'd, did want our Sauiours ayde,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſinnes, as well as ours, did make him bleed;</l>
               <l>And was the cauſe that ſtopp'd his glorious breath</l>
               <l>To ranſome them, as well as vs, from death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:19"/>
               <l>Yet will not theſe proud Phariſees be perſwaded,</l>
               <l>But vrge traditions, from their fathers taught:</l>
               <l>And haue the Goſpell through their power inuaded,</l>
               <l>And many holy needleſſe reliques ſought</l>
               <l>Of ancient Saint, and holy men deceaſed,</l>
               <l>Whereby their great Idolatry's increaſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> nor <hi>Iohn,</hi> nor reuerent <hi>Paul</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would neuer ſuffer, but denied thoſe men</l>
               <l>To offer any ſacrifice at all,</l>
               <l>Nor with the ſmalleſt worſhip honor them:</l>
               <l>Why ſhould wee thinke they craue ſuch wonderous ods,</l>
               <l>To be ador'd, or pray'd to now, like gods?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If that the Angell would not ſuffer <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Whoſe brightneſſe made him fall downe flatte before him,)</l>
               <l>Aſcribe no honor, but to God alone,</l>
               <l>Nor with diuine proſtration to adore him:</l>
               <l>Why ſhould thoſe Saints, which were but ſinful men,</l>
               <l>Deſire ſuch grace and glory done to them?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor ſure they doe not, did not ſuperſtition</l>
               <l>Broch now for doctrine, what true faith enuies;</l>
               <l>And by their Romiſh traſh make ſuch Diuiſion,</l>
               <l>Which God, Saints, Angels, heauen and all denies;</l>
               <l>Where Chriſt with them, and they with Chriſt agree</l>
               <l>To make their prayers t'only none but thee:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For him hath God the Father ſealed true,</l>
               <l>He pay'd the price, he bought vs with his blood;</l>
               <l>Then vnto him the debt is onely due,</l>
               <l>Which can in humane iuſtice be withſtood:</l>
               <l>All worſhip, prayer, praiſe, and glorie too,</l>
               <l>Belongs to him, and more then we can doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:20"/>
               <l>For there's no precept which that dutie bindes,</l>
               <l>No law that doctrine found to ratifie,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe ſome falſe zeale, and affections blinde,</l>
               <l>Should broach for truth this error firſt: for why</l>
               <l>Should not the Prophets, Patriarkes, and the reſt</l>
               <l>Be pray'd vnto, which were as highly bleſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yes ſure, their grace, their merits, and their faith</l>
               <l>Were euen as great, as were the great'ſt of them;</l>
               <l>And had as much praiſe giuen (as Scripture ſaith)</l>
               <l>Which heard, ſaw, knew, and talk'd with God like men:</l>
               <l>More loue, more grace, more fauor who hath knowne</l>
               <l>To be to any of th'Apoſtles ſhowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet Romes Towre, proud Babell will withſtand,</l>
               <l>And broach their owne inuentions for pure truth;</l>
               <l>With ſweete compounded doctrines held in hand,</l>
               <l>They cunningly beguile vnſtable youth,</l>
               <l>And doe deceiue their ſoules with name of him</l>
               <l>Which did deſcend from heauen to die for ſin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which in the habite come of harmeleſſe ſheepe,</l>
               <l>Yet are moſt ſtrange deuouring wolues within,</l>
               <l>And many holy obſeruations keepe,</l>
               <l>To varniſh out hypocriſie and ſin:</l>
               <l>They ſeeme pure Saints, but looke a little further,</l>
               <l>And you ſhal find, their poiſonings, rapes &amp; murther.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet the heau'ns their lingering vengance ſpares</l>
               <l>(Good Lord grant grace vnto thy little flocke)</l>
               <l>For to diſcerne their frauds, deceits, and ſnares</l>
               <l>And build our truſt on thee, the liuing Rocke,</l>
               <l>That ſure and certaine ground which neuer falls</l>
               <l>When theirs ſhall waſte, conſume and periſh all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:20"/>
               <l>But thou which build'ſt vpon that corner ſtone</l>
               <l>Thy faith, whoſe fruits ſo euidently appeares,</l>
               <l>And mad'ſt thy ſoules deſire to him alone,</l>
               <l>VVhich on his head a crowne of thornes did weare:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe vnpolluted conſcience better tells,</l>
               <l>That trueſt faith with grace, and vertue dwells.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And where thou ſeeſt with thoſe tranſlucent eyes,</l>
               <l>Thy Soueraigne Lord and Sauiour crown'd in glorie,</l>
               <l>VVhich all the waies of his elected tries</l>
               <l>Through pains, griefes, teares, and ſad afflictions ſtorie:</l>
               <l>The patient ſufferings of his poore elected,</l>
               <l>VVhich in this world are vil'ſt of all reſpected,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus, worthy Lady, if thy faith was weigh'd,</l>
               <l>VVith many Ladies now it would contend</l>
               <l>For crowne, and praiſe, and all their pride vpbraid,</l>
               <l>VVhich makes externall honor all their end:</l>
               <l>And glory, in the greatneſſe of their birth,</l>
               <l>Or elſe their wealth, which is as little worth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou which honor, praiſe, and glory ſings</l>
               <l>Vnto the Father of eternitie.</l>
               <l>And to his Sonne, which ſuch ſaluation brings,</l>
               <l>Crowning our faithes with immortalitie:</l>
               <l>VVere now tranſlated to that place of reſt,</l>
               <l>Ile leaue thy faith triumphing with the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to that vertue which few ladies knowes,</l>
               <l>Or at the leaſt will not acknowledge, knowne,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it loues not pride, nor Court-like ſhowes,</l>
               <l>But ſtill retires it ſelfe to liue alone,</l>
               <l>Sequeſtred from thoſe great reſorts of ſinne,</l>
               <l>VVhich many ſpend their youthfull glories in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:21"/>
               <l>Is that rich vertue, Great humilitie,</l>
               <l>Yet not too great, in great men now adayes,</l>
               <l>The onely badge of true Gentilitie;</l>
               <l>If gentle bloods would ponder all her wayes,</l>
               <l>And ſcand thy worth, or truely finde thee out,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Adams</hi> brood would neuer be ſo ſtout.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor would the mightie Monarchs tyrannize,</l>
               <l>Nor ſeeke by violence to vſurpe a crowne,</l>
               <l>Nor noble blouds their honors preiudice,</l>
               <l>In treading poore diſpiſed Orphanes downe:</l>
               <l>The <hi>quondam</hi> Farmer turn'd a gentle now,</l>
               <l>Would not vpon the backes of poore men plow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oppreſſion would not beare ſo great a hand,</l>
               <l>Nor theſe Rent-rayſers racke their tenants ground,</l>
               <l>Authoritie would not on ſuch ſtrict tearmes ſtand;</l>
               <l>Nor with his griſly lookes the weake confound:</l>
               <l>No pride, nor periuries, fraud, nor glory vaine</l>
               <l>Shall haunt thee, when this vertue thou haſt gain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The key t'vnlocke the knowledge of the minde,</l>
               <l>That all her imperfections may appeare,</l>
               <l>The ſalue to cure her eyes that were ſo blinde,</l>
               <l>The wholeſome balme to heale the deafeſt eare,</l>
               <l>The ſoueraigne cordiall which the heauens affords</l>
               <l>To mortall men, not to be ſpoke with words.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh thou which makes the heart of man as poore,</l>
               <l>As is the ſparrow on the houſes top,</l>
               <l>And commend'ſt him with feare and ſhame the more,</l>
               <l>VVhen conſcience pleads the ſinnes which he forgot:</l>
               <l>A heauie reckoning, did not heauen forgiue vs,</l>
               <l>And with their grace and mercie great relieue vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:21"/>
               <l>Thou which pul'dſt downe the proud aſpiring ſpirit,</l>
               <l>And makes it leuell with the low eſtate;</l>
               <l>Confoundeſt naturall pride, wit, ſtrength, and merit,</l>
               <l>An leaueſt humane worth cleane deſolate:</l>
               <l>Rob'ſt vs of power, and workes, to build our truſt,</l>
               <l>Not in our ſelues, but Ieſus Chriſt the Iuſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou Queene of vertues, and the onely guide</l>
               <l>VVhich lead'ſt this ladie to that heauenly rode;</l>
               <l>And that meane path ſo oppoſite to pride,</l>
               <l>VVhich in theſe ſinfull times but few haue trode:</l>
               <l>The reines, which bridles Natures power, &amp; tels the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>How vile a ſinne ambition is, and ſwels them:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou whoſe low ſpirit, meeke heart, and humble minde</l>
               <l>Did crowne the Conquereſſe o're the crowne of pride,</l>
               <l>Thou which did'ſt loſe theſe toyes, thoſe ioyes to finde,</l>
               <l>And haſt thy ſelfe, within thy ſelfe, denide.</l>
               <l>Haſt found by meekeneſſe, honor; reſt for croſſes,</l>
               <l>Ioyes for thy ſorrowe profit for thy loſſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So gentle, curteous, affable and kinde,</l>
               <l>That moſt would think it would diſgrace their honor,</l>
               <l>If they ſhould beare but ſuch a lowly minde</l>
               <l>And much renowne and dignitie take from her:</l>
               <l>As not to vſe that ſtate to her belongs,</l>
               <l>Impaire her worth, and noble honor wrongs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why ſhould not perſons of the nobleſt ſtraine</l>
               <l>Their honors vſe, their ſtate and name vphold?</l>
               <l>Why ſhould they not their glory great maintaine,</l>
               <l>As well as their forefathers did of old?</l>
               <l>It is their owne, and they were borne vnto it,</l>
               <l>Why is it counted pride in them to doe it?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:22"/>
               <l>'Tis true great Ladie I do know no cauſe,</l>
               <l>If honor in it ſelfe doth liue confinde:</l>
               <l>Nor breakes not iuſtice, loue, nor natures lawes,</l>
               <l>Which ſauadge beaſts in ſome affections binde:</l>
               <l>That hath well learn'd to know and rule himſelfe,</l>
               <l>Imbracing vertue, and contemning pelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But they that glory in their ſtate and greatneſſe,</l>
               <l>And gentle curteſie, count baſe ſlauery,</l>
               <l>Which holds the higheſt pride, but cleanly neatneſſe;</l>
               <l>And their ſtrong Tyranny, braue validity:</l>
               <l>Nor in his nature's found but little good,</l>
               <l>What profit is their in this noble blood?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What houſe ſo famous that did not begin,</l>
               <l>And from moſt meeke and worthy mindes proceede?</l>
               <l>Which did at firſt their braue achiuements win,</l>
               <l>From vertues time and honorable deeds:</l>
               <l>If it be ſo why ſhould not humble ſpirits</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſe vs ſtill, like glory to inherit?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſuch are the vilde cuſtomes of theſe times,</l>
               <l>That vertue is aſham'd, her ſelfe to knowe,</l>
               <l>She ſhall be taxt, ſhe feares for ſome baſe ruines,</l>
               <l>If their full power, and grace ſhe publicke ſhewes:</l>
               <l>Vertue muſt weare the cloak of vice about her,</l>
               <l>Or elſe your greateſt gallants will but flout her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis now diſhonor to be honorable,</l>
               <l>And right muſt now indure a little wrong:</l>
               <l>Truth like the times muſt change, or be vnſtable,</l>
               <l>Or elſe ſhe muſt but whiſper with her tongue:</l>
               <l>Loue, pitty, charity, if they want, I feare,</l>
               <l>Muſt get their liuinh where they cannot heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:22"/>
               <l>Well could thy better guided ſpirits approue</l>
               <l>To kepe a meane gate in an humble path,</l>
               <l>And not to climbe thoſe lofty ſeates aboue,</l>
               <l>Which many cares and diſcontentments hath,</l>
               <l>Whereof Dame fortune queene of cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge doth raigne;</l>
               <l>And who ſhe liſt ſhall vp, then downe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſtill pure heau'ns thy honor did preſerue,</l>
               <l>Clad in thoſe humble garments Chriſt did weare,</l>
               <l>From which thy vertuous minde did neuer ſwarue:</l>
               <l>But ſtill a gentle ſpirit did'ſt loue and beare,</l>
               <l>And neuer hadſt this leſſon far to ſeeke,</l>
               <l>Come learne of me that humble am, and meeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But hadſt both read, and knowne from the beginning,</l>
               <l>How grace attends the one, and ſhame the other,</l>
               <l>Greatneſſe, and honors are ſuch ſpurres to ſinning,</l>
               <l>And there's no vice ſo great, but pride can couer:</l>
               <l>Humility, the firſt true leſſon learnes vs,</l>
               <l>How we ſhould know our ſelues, &amp; beſt diſcernes vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In thy faire breſt this vertue fixed lies,</l>
               <l>Which like a pretious Iewell doth adorne thee,</l>
               <l>And as a chaine thoſe other graces ties,</l>
               <l>Which through the earth with ſuch renowne hath borne thee</l>
               <l>With mounting <hi>Icarus</hi> doeſt feare no fall,</l>
               <l>Nor yet ſeekes meanes to raiſe thy ſtate at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Lady whoſe rare vertues paſſing thought,</l>
               <l>And weake imagination can't attaine:</l>
               <l>A prize for mortall men too dearely bought,</l>
               <l>And which the Gods themſelues can beſt maintaine:</l>
               <l>For who can tell the ſpirits power that's giuen,</l>
               <l>From that all powerfull power, the king of heauen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:23"/>
               <l>Thou which didſt ſeeke to hide thy honour great,</l>
               <l>Lapt vp from fame within our countries armes,</l>
               <l>To keepe with vs thy reſidentall ſeate,</l>
               <l>So faire and ſure from high aſpiring harmes:</l>
               <l>Suppreſſing by a life retir'd that gueſt,</l>
               <l>Which crown's thee with more glory, then the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, that true honor which from vertue ſprings,</l>
               <l>Like to a ſparke will kindle without blowing,</l>
               <l>Or like a tree which fruite in autumne brings,</l>
               <l>That ſpite of winters rage is euer growing,</l>
               <l>And fills the owners breſt with glory ſtore,</l>
               <l>That Kings ne're knew, nor yet poſſeſt before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whilſt thoſe that liue in greateſt Monarches grace,</l>
               <l>And ſit vpon the pinacle of fame,</l>
               <l>That fortune at their pleaſure can imbrace,</l>
               <l>And thinke to get a neuer dying name:</l>
               <l>Haue not to halfe thy praiſe with all their paines,</l>
               <l>Arriu'd vnto, which thou vnſought for gaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy humble life like to thy Sauiour led,</l>
               <l>In greateſt greatneſſe meeke, in plentie poore</l>
               <l>Did make thy fame renowne and honor ſpred,</l>
               <l>And did increaſe thy prayſes more and more,</l>
               <l>That in concealing as the worthieſt vſes,</l>
               <l>Thy honors grace thee, and more grace infuſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou didſt not beare a loftie ſcornefull eye,</l>
               <l>Nor glory in the greatneſſe of thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>Nor exerciſe thy minde in things too high:</l>
               <l>But vnder-ualueſt what moſt highly rate,</l>
               <l>And mad'ſt thy minde, a map for all to ſee</l>
               <l>The ſtraine of vertue, in gentility.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:23"/>
               <l>Thus did thy humble life in high degree,</l>
               <l>Raiſe thy vnwilling minde to more renowne,</l>
               <l>Induing thee with greater dignitie,</l>
               <l>Then thoſe that with mo worldly pomp were crown'd,</l>
               <l>For thine were true, and did from vertue growe,</l>
               <l>Elſe heauen &amp; earth, would ne'r haue grac't them ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for her temperance in attire and diet,</l>
               <l>Which ſhew how much ſhe worldly pompe diſpiſed,</l>
               <l>And free from that ſuper-abounding riot,</l>
               <l>Which is by ſome to prodigall bloods deuiſed,</l>
               <l>So ſtrict vnto her ſelfe to others free,</l>
               <l>That gaue content in liberallity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And which did liue confinde in her eſtate,</l>
               <l>Not prodigally to waſt in ſurfets ſtore,</l>
               <l>Nor after ſuch a vild luxurious rate,</l>
               <l>To pamper fleſh with cloide delights the more:</l>
               <l>But kept a better courſe, and ſhun'd thoſe ſinnes,</l>
               <l>Which curious and delightfull appetites brings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whilſt ſome in beaſtly Epicuriſme ſpend,</l>
               <l>And waſte their daies in vild licentiouſnes,</l>
               <l>Glutting inſatiate taſts, but to offend,</l>
               <l>And make their God their bellies for exceſſe,</l>
               <l>Which eate, &amp; drinke, &amp; ſpend their time like ſlaues,</l>
               <l>To fatten ſin, wormes, Sathan, and the graues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whilſt ſhe did vſe the meanes that might procure,</l>
               <l>The leaſt offence that could be giuen in this,</l>
               <l>No ſuch delitious bayts could her allure,</l>
               <l>T'abuſe heauens gift in vſing them amiſſe;</l>
               <l>But did obſerue and keepe ſo true a diet,</l>
               <l>As kept her health full, and her ſoule in quiet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:24"/>
               <l>What Abſtinence hath ſhe vſ'd to ſubdue</l>
               <l>Thoſe cauſes, &amp; thoſe motions which might tempt her</l>
               <l>To make her proue vnto her ſelfe vntrue,</l>
               <l>Or with the taſt of follow could preuent her,</l>
               <l>Oh no who ſtriues that glorious marke to win,</l>
               <l>Muſt fly the meanes, as well as fly the ſin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What man that open lies vnto his foes,</l>
               <l>From dangers and diſgraces can be free,</l>
               <l>What man that with his enemies walkes and goes,</l>
               <l>That can ſtand firme, and neuer conquered be?</l>
               <l>What man that graſpes ſin in his wanton armes,</l>
               <l>Can free eſcape, and ne're be toucht with harmes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh no it is too hard for fleſh and blood,</l>
               <l>If heau'ns ſhould vs with our owne frailties truſt,</l>
               <l>We ſhould come ſhort for to performe that good,</l>
               <l>Alas what power and ſtrength doth lie in duſt,</l>
               <l>When euery winde, blaſt, tempeſt, ſtorme, &amp; weather,</l>
               <l>Blowes vs away far lighter then a feather?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good Lady how far was thou bleſt aboue vs,</l>
               <l>That could ſo moderate thy affections here:</l>
               <l>Where thy example is enough to moue vs,</l>
               <l>If any loue, zeale, grace and heauenly feare</l>
               <l>Were wrought in this obdurate heart of ours,</l>
               <l>To make vs better ſerue th'eternall powers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ciuill block not larded with much coſt,</l>
               <l>Nor wrought with broadered worke moſt curiouſly,</l>
               <l>Whereby ſome haue both wealth and credit loſt,</l>
               <l>A iuſt reward for thoughts that mount too high,</l>
               <l>Could not ſurprize, nor in ſubiection bring,</l>
               <l>Her minde at all to like ſo vaine a thing,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:24"/>
               <l>For well ſhe knew that fleſh and blood is apt</l>
               <l>Of it owne nature to be proud enough,</l>
               <l>And needs not ſuch inticements to intrap,</l>
               <l>As cloth of Tiſſue, gold, or richer ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>Which often makes the wearer wondrous proud,</l>
               <l>Though 'tis for Kings, and princes courts allowd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet for thoſe men that can direct their minds,</l>
               <l>Whoſe gentle ſpirits in vertue haue bin bred,</l>
               <l>And by deſarts haue vnto honor climb'd:</l>
               <l>Such coſtly garments haue bene giuen and red.</l>
               <l>But vpſtarts now haue tooke that glory from her,</l>
               <l>Moſt imitate the faſhion, few the honor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſhe which for this vertue liues a wonder,</l>
               <l>Laſhes not looſly into ſuch extreames:</l>
               <l>But keeps without conſtraint her greatneſſe vnder,</l>
               <l>And with her honor and her ſtate diſpneſes,</l>
               <l>Fitting her habit euer to her minde,</l>
               <l>Moſt ciuill, modeſt, pure of vertues kinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She decks not out with gawdy oſtentation,</l>
               <l>This earthly ſubſtance to be gaz'd vpon,</l>
               <l>No new inuentions, and diſſtinguiſh'd faſhion,</l>
               <l>Theſe changing times can tempt her to put on:</l>
               <l>But liues alone makes vertue all her gaine,</l>
               <l>Deſpiſing worldly pompe and glory vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She couets not this popular admiration,</l>
               <l>The which ambitious nations moſt deſire</l>
               <l>Nor makes her glory this worlds reputation,</l>
               <l>Which ſets the heart of men ſo much on fire,</l>
               <l>Nor ſtands on honors, titles, nor renowne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe broken truſt hath caſt a number downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:25"/>
               <l>Nor doth ſhe ſpend her time like ſome of thoſe,</l>
               <l>In dreſſing, trimming, varniſhing of beauty,</l>
               <l>Wherein too many doe ſuch truſt repoſe,</l>
               <l>They cleane forget all heauenly loue and duty,</l>
               <l>And ſpend their deereſt howers, and ſweeteſt daies,</l>
               <l>In flouriſhing that faire, which ſoone decaies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay which is worſe, a lamentable caſe,</l>
               <l>Some new complexious and adulterous art;</l>
               <l>They can deuiſe to paint their fading face,</l>
               <l>And helpe that worke which nature doth impart,</l>
               <l>Whoſe dambd inuentions ſeekes to mend that hew,</l>
               <l>Whom heauen at firſt did make moſt beſt and true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And pamper vp the fleſh in all delights,</l>
               <l>And ſooth their pleaſures, in what they doe craue,</l>
               <l>Which in vaine ſtudies ſpend whole daies and nights;</l>
               <l>What diet, faſhion, and attire to haue:</l>
               <l>Conſuming halfe their time in flattering glaſſes,</l>
               <l>To idolize that which is duſt and aſhes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which trim, and dreſſe with artificiall ſhapes</l>
               <l>Their painted bodies like to rotten combs,</l>
               <l>And onely but for worldy glory gapes,</l>
               <l>As if they ſprung not from corrupted wombs,</l>
               <l>But had ſome priuiledge both from heauen &amp; nature</l>
               <l>To be adored like Gods, not mottall creatures.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe proud ambitious thoughts do ſwell ſo high,</l>
               <l>They thinke no mortall worthy to come neere them,</l>
               <l>But they muſt crouch or kneele ſubmiſſiuely,</l>
               <l>Their looks and greatnes makes them ſo to feare them,</l>
               <l>That ſcarce a furlongs diſtance will content them,</l>
               <l>f proſtrate duty be not done, and ſent them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:25"/>
               <l>Nay, when they'aue done the beſt, and all they can,</l>
               <l>If grace, ſpeech, action, doth not well adorne him,</l>
               <l>And rareſt geſture, art can giue to man,</l>
               <l>The'le hold him for a ſeruile clowne, and ſcorne him,</l>
               <l>His duty and behauiour comes far ſhort,</l>
               <l>To grace ſuch honors as attends the Court.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yee glorious heau'ns to whom all honor's due,</l>
               <l>Yee blinde vs not to ſuch ſtrict ſeruice here</l>
               <l>So that our hearts be firme, vpright, and true,</l>
               <l>And your great reuerent name doth loue and feare:</l>
               <l>Theſe outward duties yee did ne're require:</l>
               <l>Which greateſt bloods, and mightieſt men deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet there be duties, would but true ones ſerue them,</l>
               <l>That none in humaine iuſtice can deny,</l>
               <l>For to be giuen to thoſe that beſt deſerue them,</l>
               <l>And keepe their thoughts from mounting vp too high,</l>
               <l>But if they once abuſe them dutie flies,</l>
               <l>And flatterers ſtraight doe ſooth them vp with lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat will this age come to, will it not burſt</l>
               <l>With vice, and ſinne, and ſplit it ſelfe a ſunder,</l>
               <l>Can patient heauens forbeare their lingring curſe,</l>
               <l>And not with ſpeedy vengeance quickly thunder:</l>
               <l>Then truth and conſcience, iuſtice, loue, and pitty,</l>
               <l>Fly quickly hence to that eternall citty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For here is no reſpect, nor friendſhip dwelling,</l>
               <l>For any of you clad in pouerty,</l>
               <l>It is ingroſt quite vp by all mens telling,</l>
               <l>Within the cloſſet of eternitie,</l>
               <l>Where they doe dwell ſithence as little worth:</l>
               <l>Till Chriſt doth come againe to iudge the earth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:26"/>
               <l>Art thou a Lady great in birth and honor,</l>
               <l>Art thou of ſtate, ranke, meanes to equall others?</l>
               <l>Then why ſhould'ſt thou take any glory from her,</l>
               <l>Or by obſcurity thus thy greatneſſe ſmother:</l>
               <l>Is there a better honor bred within thee,</l>
               <l>That from theſe worldly honors thus can win thee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet Lady had thy neuer ranging eye,</l>
               <l>Tooke but a viewe of what they might behold,</l>
               <l>How many vanities might they ſoone deſcrie,</l>
               <l>Which nature needs not, dayly to be ſold?</l>
               <l>Where more ſpent far in ſuperfluitie,</l>
               <l>Then would ſome nature in neceſſitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou which from theſe vaine delights didſt flie,</l>
               <l>And little knowes the vices of theſe times,</l>
               <l>Clos'd vp in one roome from ſocietie,</l>
               <l>In better ſtudies and in arts diuine,</l>
               <l>Didſt ſhew thy temperance from all worldly ioyes,</l>
               <l>And thoſe falſe baytes which many minds annoyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus didſt thou ſpend thy pretious howers and time,</l>
               <l>In reading vertuous and moſt ſacred bookes,</l>
               <l>And truly ſeruing of the powers diuine,</l>
               <l>Nor to theſe worldly vanities once lookes,</l>
               <l>Wherewith thou hadſt continuall warre and ſtrife</l>
               <l>Which crownes thee ſuch a meritorious wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her ſenſes were not organs vnto folly,</l>
               <l>Nor conducts to receiue in vanitie,</l>
               <l>Theſe outward entrances ſhe kept more holy,</l>
               <l>And not expos'd to worldly amitie.</l>
               <l>But for heauens zeale, and glory ſtopt thoſe ſluces,</l>
               <l>And bars the paſſage which might cauſe abuſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:26"/>
               <l>Nor did her eares itch after nouelties,</l>
               <l>Nor yet inquiſitiue was in curious matters:</l>
               <l>But ere reſtraine thoſe powers and faculties,</l>
               <l>From ſmoth tongud Gnatoes which are vſ'd to flatter,</l>
               <l>Whoſe whiſpring to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues if that they once come neer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Will ſtrait infect them, if they deigne to heare them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And like to hony drop into their eares,</l>
               <l>That poyſon which ſoone ſwell ambitious ſpirits,</l>
               <l>That nothing elſe they doe deſire to heare,</l>
               <l>But their owne praiſes, honors, worth, and merits,</l>
               <l>And rockt aſleepe in their ſecuritie,</l>
               <l>Make themſelues equall to the deitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh had but great men or great princes courts,</l>
               <l>Bene free from this how happy had they bin?</l>
               <l>Such treaſons, maſſacres, and plots of ſundry ſorts,</l>
               <l>None had contriu'd to ſnare the mighty in,</l>
               <l>They might haue ſtept ſecurely without feares,</l>
               <l>Had not this rancker crept into their eares,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh ſnare to honor, ſtayne to noble blood</l>
               <l>Thou great diſeaſe, obſequious adulation,</l>
               <l>Which Vulter-like doeſt feede vppon the good,</l>
               <l>And preys vppon them in ſo faire a faſhion,</l>
               <l>That thou doeſt bite by fawning, kil'ſt by ſmiling,</l>
               <l>Strangl'ſt by loue, and by moſt truſt beguiling.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſhe which loues not no ſuch Sirens ſinging,</l>
               <l>Doth tune far better muſick to her minde,</l>
               <l>And knowes thoſe rare contents, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts bringing,</l>
               <l>With all thoſe ioyes which thoſe that proue them finde</l>
               <l>Whilſt many cares and troubles vext their ſpirits,</l>
               <l>Which hunt for praiſe, and glorie vaine inherits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:27"/>
               <l>And waſte their bodies and their ſoules together,</l>
               <l>To compaſſe here this windy blaſt of praiſe,</l>
               <l>Which hauing got they haue but caught a feather,</l>
               <l>And like to ſmoake, and vapours ſoone decaies,</l>
               <l>But thoſe whom trueſt fame and vertue raiſes,</l>
               <l>Ne're luls themſelues a ſleepe with their owne prayſes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pardon great Lady my vnworthy quill,</l>
               <l>That it ſhould doe thy name, and honor wrong.</l>
               <l>And looke not to my art, but to my will,</l>
               <l>Which more affords then can be told with tongue:</l>
               <l>What learning wants, let ſomething elſe ſupply,</l>
               <l>I know his pitch is for my reatch to high.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She that did liue ſo long, and rule alone,</l>
               <l>And fairely did ſupport her houſes fame,</l>
               <l>A widdow, wife, and maide, confinde in one,</l>
               <l>In all, and ſeuerall ſtates ſo free from blame,</l>
               <l>That enuy, nor the iniurious hand of time,</l>
               <l>Could euer ſtaine, or touch with any crime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her thoughts ſo continent, and her chaſt deſires,</l>
               <l>Which neuer rioted in exppenſe of time,</l>
               <l>Sprung from thoſe true eternall liuing fires,</l>
               <l>Which doth all vertue to it ſelfe combine</l>
               <l>Not lightly led, nor ſtarting now and then</l>
               <l>To place new fancies in affecting men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But truely kept her ſelfe vnto her loue,</l>
               <l>Her worthy loue, in youth, in age, in death:</l>
               <l>So conſtant, faithfull, true as turtle doue,</l>
               <l>Where her affections gaue no ſecond breath:</l>
               <l>But liu'd in one pure loue, and neuer changed,</l>
               <l>In thoughts ſo firmly knit, they neuer ranged.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:27"/>
               <l>Which for the ſpace of almoſt thirty yeares,</l>
               <l>Did rule alone her houſe admir,d of many,</l>
               <l>Such holy graces in her life appeares;</l>
               <l>Such perfect vertues ſeldome ſeene in any:</l>
               <l>A virgin, wife, a widow, maide, to be,</l>
               <l>So old in honor, yet from folly free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Could not her long deceaſed ſpouſe before,</l>
               <l>Grac'd with ſo many worthy after loues,</l>
               <l>Nor time, nor nature which could argue more,</l>
               <l>Nor any thing from that ſtrict courſe remoue:</l>
               <l>But ſtill her reſolution doth perſeuer,</l>
               <l>Inuiolate vnto the firſt for euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why then poore pen doeſt thou attempt ſo far,</l>
               <l>And canſt not touch the riches of her honor,</l>
               <l>Nor nothing neere deſcribe this glorious ſtarre:</l>
               <l>But rather much vnhidden worth take from her,</l>
               <l>The little world of thy poore wit on fire,</l>
               <l>Will rather burne then ſatisfie deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet giue me leaue great Readers to admire,</l>
               <l>Faire imitators of her honors worth;</l>
               <l>Although I cannot ſatisfie deſire,</l>
               <l>Nor ſet her high deſarts, and honor forth,</l>
               <l>Accept my will, which muſt remaine your debtor,</l>
               <l>Till time, or heau'ns ſhall grace me to ſing better.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She in whoſe breaſt, grace ſuch impreſſion tooke,</l>
               <l>That made her time not like a mortall creature;</l>
               <l>Which honors, ſtate, and dignities forſooke,</l>
               <l>A thing moſt hard and wondrous ſtrange to nature,</l>
               <l>That vertue ſhould be found for to contemne,</l>
               <l>Such meanes and fortunes, as aduanceth them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:28"/>
               <l>Could grace and vertue natures force expell,</l>
               <l>And breake thoſe lawes wherein ſhe binds too many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Could heauenly gifts in ſuch a concord dwell,</l>
               <l>So welbelou'd within the heart of any:</l>
               <l>That in ſo many daies they ſhould not fall,</l>
               <l>Nor yet be toucht with any crime at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pure-thoughted Lady which preſerues thy ſoule</l>
               <l>So cleane from fleſhly crimes, and carnall pleaſures,</l>
               <l>Nor didſt conſent vnto ſuch actions foule,</l>
               <l>Wherein too many wallow out of meaſure,</l>
               <l>That inbred ſin which neuer leaues the moſt,</l>
               <l>Till nature's ready to yeeld vp the ghoaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One loue thy ſoule delighted, which deceaſe,</l>
               <l>Did liue a freſh in the ſtill vndiuided.</l>
               <l>Two perſons ioynd in one makes no releaſe</l>
               <l>Till both be dead in loue ſo firmly guided,</l>
               <l>Death parts the body, but the ſoule doth honor,</l>
               <l>In ſhadie groues to meete ſo true a louer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So conſtant Lady thou which after death,</l>
               <l>In ſtrengh of yeares to no ſuch bayts did yeeld,</l>
               <l>Gaines fame a ſecond life, and longer breath,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtedfaſt loue, on better ground did build,</l>
               <l>Where palmes of victorie in thy hands are found,</l>
               <l>And lawrell wreaths to girt thy temples round.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where thou <hi>Diana</hi>-like didſt lead a life,</l>
               <l>In ſacred loue mixt with moſt chaſt deſire,</l>
               <l>Or like thoſe holy veſtalls void of ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Which keepes their honors ſpotleſſe, and intire,</l>
               <l>And neuer lookes ſo true a courſe they liue,</l>
               <l>To thoſe inchantments which the world doth giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:28"/>
               <l>Where pureſt loue like to the morning dew,</l>
               <l>Sent downe from him which all good gifts infuſes,</l>
               <l>Inioyes thoſe rare contents giuen but to few,</l>
               <l>To very few which worldly traffique vſes,</l>
               <l>So great and meeke, ſo chaſt, and yet a wife,</l>
               <l>For not a mortals, but an Angels life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which onely keeps not from ſocietie,</l>
               <l>Thy perſon free, but quencht thoſe inward fires,</l>
               <l>And from looſe thoughts, and vaine delights didſt flie,</l>
               <l>Hating th'imbracements of vnchaſt deſires</l>
               <l>And gaue no place to ſuch inticements vaine,</l>
               <l>Which proues the owners loſſe, the actors paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How canſt thou then great Lady all forſake,</l>
               <l>So many thouſand bayted hopes to ſee,</l>
               <l>And many great ones little reſt to take,</l>
               <l>Whilſt thou ſecurely ſleeps from dangers free?</l>
               <l>No thy chaſt boſome neuer luſted ſo,</l>
               <l>To looſe a freind for to imbrace a foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou worthy patterne of this wanton age,</l>
               <l>Whoſe pure affections diſpoſſeſſeth ſin,</l>
               <l>And acts thy part vpon this earthly ſtage,</l>
               <l>As chaſt as ſhe whoſe loue <hi>Troy</hi> towne did win:</l>
               <l>Oh who would wiſh more honor in this life,</l>
               <l>Then die a vertuous widow, virgin, wife?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou mighſt haue knit thy ſelfe in ſacred bands,</l>
               <l>With honorable perſons in degree,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Hymens</hi> rites vniting hearts and hands,</l>
               <l>And not haue wrong this firſt loue being free,</l>
               <l>Oh but thy ſoule ſayes to thy ſelfe alone,</l>
               <l>That fayth moſt firme, that keeps it ſelfe to one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:29"/>
               <l>No friend nor louer ſince thy boſome ſmothers,</l>
               <l>But Chriſt thy Sauiour, ſpouſe, and husband deare,</l>
               <l>For whoſe deare ſake thou haſt forſooke all others,</l>
               <l>How great, or rich ſo e're they liued here;</l>
               <l>And ſworne vnto thy ſelfe, and made a vow</l>
               <l>To ſerue, loue, feare, and keepe him onely now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh happy choyſe, yet man and wife do varry,</l>
               <l>From theſe pure paths, which vnto vertue tends,</l>
               <l>They care not who, nor yet how oft they marry</l>
               <l>For loue of lucre, luſt, or worldy freinds:</l>
               <l>Exchanging oft the better for the worſe,</l>
               <l>Who weds a ſecond neuer lou'd the firſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such ſoule reſpects are ſo ingrauen in vs,</l>
               <l>Firſt beauty, that faire obiect doth allure vs.</l>
               <l>Then mighty friends in ſtate or meanes doth win vs,</l>
               <l>That from inſuing dangers may ſecure vs:</l>
               <l>But laſt and greateſt is wealth, reuenewes, riches,</l>
               <l>The which the ſoules of men ſo much bewiches.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long maiſt thou liue in thy more happier choiſe,</l>
               <l>That euerlaſting loue which fadeth neuer,</l>
               <l>Long mayſt thou, with that Bridegroome faire reioice,</l>
               <l>In thoſe triumphing ioyes which laſteth euer,</l>
               <l>Long maiſt thou honor, praiſe and glory ſing,</l>
               <l>Vnto the ſoueraigne Lord, the King of Kings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where thy pure thoughts, chaſt boſome, vertuous life,</l>
               <l>Weds thy vnſpotted ſoule to endleſſe ioyes:</l>
               <l>Whoſe loue to that great ſpouſe makes a chaſt wife,</l>
               <l>And whoſe rare gifts weake fleſh and bloud deſtroyes:</l>
               <l>Whoſe outward honors many equals finde,</l>
               <l>But few to match the honor of the minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:29"/>
               <l>Why ſhould my ſtriuing pen deſire to tell,</l>
               <l>What it by force cannot attaine to know?</l>
               <l>Why ſhould my will againſt my skill rebell,</l>
               <l>My paſſions thus 'gainſt reaſons lawes to ſhow?</l>
               <l>What ardent furies workes within my minde,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke for that no wit, nor toile can finde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh giue me leaue to breake off, thou my Muſe,</l>
               <l>I cannot diue ſo deepe, I may be drown'd,</l>
               <l>Then ſpare my weakeneſſe, and defects excuſe,</l>
               <l>Which muſt retire when it can feele no ground:</l>
               <l>That glorious ſtreame of honor 'tis too deepe</l>
               <l>For my weake braine, aboue the waues to keepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet her bountie doth inuite my pen,</l>
               <l>That vertue which doth challenge praiſe with beſt,</l>
               <l>And vrges my dull hand to write agen,</l>
               <l>Which crownes her with more glory then the reſt,</l>
               <l>And makes her name and honor mount the higher</l>
               <l>With ſuch great grace, as makes the world admire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her bountie, <hi>Alexander</hi>-like, did win</l>
               <l>A generall loue, and liking of the beſt;</l>
               <l>Her fame and honor doth but now begin,</l>
               <l>As if no worthy gifts had fill'd her breſt,</l>
               <l>And ſhee had not been fraught with ſuch great ſtore</l>
               <l>Of vertuous parts, in all her life before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heere Fame and Bountie are at ſtrife together,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall excell each other in their praiſe;</l>
               <l>Such copious matter both affords, that neither</l>
               <l>I cannot tell her worth, will higheſt raiſe:</l>
               <l>Both ſpeakes ſo well, that I will doubtfull leaue it.</l>
               <l>Vnto the world that better can conceiue it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:30"/>
               <l>Yet in the booke of true recording fame,</l>
               <l>Such mightie volumes of her vertues ſtand,</l>
               <l>Moſt fairely drawne by ancient time, which came</l>
               <l>Attented with a faire incompaſs'd band</l>
               <l>Of minutes, houres, daies, weeks, months and years,</l>
               <l>And ſpoke a ſpeech that rauiſh'd humane eares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I that fell downe at that moſt pleaſant ſpring,</l>
               <l>Make my petition vnto aged Time,</l>
               <l>That he would ope the booke againe, and ſing</l>
               <l>Thoſe too much bleſſed words, and crowned lines:</l>
               <l>Whereat he ſmilde at th' weakneſſe of my braine,</l>
               <l>And ſaid 'twas more then nature could containe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For in deepe characters heere doth lie inrol'd</l>
               <l>The famous Arts and memorable deeds</l>
               <l>Of all thoſe worthies which haue beene of old,</l>
               <l>Which from faire Vertues line and ſtocke proceeds:</l>
               <l>The monuments of Fame, which through my hand,</l>
               <l>For ruſtie age haue beene forgotten long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where ſhee amongſt the reſt of honors line,</l>
               <l>Lies ſurely writ in thoſe eternall ſcrowles,</l>
               <l>Inrol'd in thoſe great monuments diuine,</l>
               <l>Which true and euerlaſting fame in rolls:</l>
               <l>In heau'ns great ſtore-houſe lock'd, till fatall doome,</l>
               <l>Raiſes her body from this earthly tombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where her moſt bounteous and munificent hand,</l>
               <l>Which neuer turn'd vnto her ſelfe in vaine,</l>
               <l>Did more affection in our ſoyle command,</l>
               <l>Then thought can thinke, or honor can obtaine:</l>
               <l>Made friend of foes, and feared loue combines</l>
               <l>In thoſe that loue, but miſerable mindes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:30"/>
               <l>For Bountie is a key that will vnlocke,</l>
               <l>And mollifie the cruell'ſt diſpoſitions,</l>
               <l>Able for to diſſolue the hardeſt rocke,</l>
               <l>And make it flexible to th'mild'ſt condition:</l>
               <l>For none, I thinke, ſo obdurate e're haue bin,</l>
               <l>But bounteous deeds, or liberall gifts could win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For 'tis a badge of Chriſtianitie,</l>
               <l>A cognizance to know rhe noble natures,</l>
               <l>The trueſt touchſtone whereby we may trie</l>
               <l>The generous race, from baſe and worldly creatures:</l>
               <l>Whoſe greedie cares doe eate the ſoule like ruſt,</l>
               <l>And neuer leaues, till leaue them needs it muſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſinne of Auarice makes vs like to hogges,</l>
               <l>Which roots i'th earth, and digs i'th ground for gaine,</l>
               <l>And with a thouſand feares our conſcience clogges,</l>
               <l>Vexing our ſpirits with long, leane, pining paines:</l>
               <l>Which like a mad conſumption waſteth all,</l>
               <l>Both ſoule and body, for a riſing fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That like a vulture, feeds vpon the liuer,</l>
               <l>And gnawes the intralls like a pining ſickneſſe,</l>
               <l>Which, where it once poſſeſſes, leaueth neuer,</l>
               <l>Take the yong man i'th Goſpell for a witneſſe:</l>
               <l>For this rancke age is much farre worſe then him</l>
               <l>Which kept the Law, and was not ſtay'd with ſin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He ſomething had to anſwere for himſelfe,</l>
               <l>And iuſtifie him for this life of ours;</l>
               <l>Had not he beene in loue with worldly pelfe,</l>
               <l>A clearer light ſhin'd not in humane powers:</l>
               <l>For who can tell that he hath done ſo well</l>
               <l>As this rich yong man, that is gone to hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:31"/>
               <l>Oh no, deare heauens, in mercie looke vpon vs,</l>
               <l>One of a thouſand cannot ſay ſo much,</l>
               <l>Yet doe not take thy grace and fauour from vs,</l>
               <l>Although ſo pure a life we cannot touch:</l>
               <l>For we renounce our ſelues, and truſt in thee,</l>
               <l>Out of this mortall toile to ſet vs free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, noble Bounty, I muſt needs commend thee,</l>
               <l>If that no other cauſe were giuen but this,</l>
               <l>And with more praiſe, then I can giue, commend thee,</l>
               <l>Which had he knowne, of heauen he could not miſſe:</l>
               <l>If for one ſinne, heauens caſt this man away,</l>
               <l>VVhat ſhall we doe, that ſinne thus euery day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVell may the greatneſſe of this vertue moue vs,</l>
               <l>And pricke vs forward, Bountie to embrace,</l>
               <l>VVhich generally doth make the world to loue vs,</l>
               <l>But moſt thoſe men of greateſt birth and place:</l>
               <l>If Auarice be ſo great and vile a ſinne,</l>
               <l>VVhat praiſe and glory then ſhall bountie winne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great honors mirror, in whom I doe finde</l>
               <l>Such rare perfection, that my ſoule admires it:</l>
               <l>Thy vertues marching in their ſeuerall kinde;</l>
               <l>That thoſe that heares it, more &amp; more deſires it:</l>
               <l>And glutted pen doth ſurfeit with the ſtore</l>
               <l>Of thoſe rich vertues, Ignorance makes poore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her bounteous hand, and great rewarding minde,</l>
               <l>VVhat pen from you, can well the ſame expreſſe,</l>
               <l>As thy true merits, and deſarts doth binde,</l>
               <l>And not eclypſe the ſame, and make them leſſe:</l>
               <l>If thoſe that tread the tract of honor true,</l>
               <l>Deſerue a golden pen, it falls to you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:31"/>
               <l>VVhere though thy ſoule hath reacht eternitie,</l>
               <l>And thou art there inrol'd in ioy and glorie:</l>
               <l>Yet giue thy ſeruant leaue, his wits to trie,</l>
               <l>And write inſuing times this ſacred ſtorie:</l>
               <l>For heauens decreed ſuch vertues ne're ſhould die,</l>
               <l>Nor ſuch bright honors taſte mortalitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet there be ſome, whom my concealing pen,</l>
               <l>For breuities, and for manners ſake omit</l>
               <l>That caries vertues, or ſhould carry them,</l>
               <l>VVhich can themſelues, and vertue too forget,</l>
               <l>And can, ſince honors hand did them preferre,</l>
               <l>Take eaſe and pleaſure, and not thinke of her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhoſe power as weake, as others were before,</l>
               <l>Now fully fed, can ſwell, and keepe no bounds,</l>
               <l>And moſt inſatiate, couet more and more,</l>
               <l>That ſhould not be in arte and learning found:</l>
               <l>VVhich once for halfe that meanes would humbly bow,</l>
               <l>VVhere hauing all, are not contented now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet, bounteous Lady, let not this thing grieue thee,</l>
               <l>That Benefactors are ſo ill reſpected,</l>
               <l>But let thy innocence in this cauſe relieue thee;</l>
               <l>Chriſt had but twelue, yet was by one neglected:</l>
               <l>If one from him, needs more muſt fall from thee,</l>
               <l>VVhich being once dead, their loyalties cannot ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis our corruptions that is bred within vs,</l>
               <l>VVhich is the cauſe of this, and hath beene euer;</l>
               <l>And preſent profit hath ſuch power to winne vs,</l>
               <l>That dead and gone, we ſtraight forget the giuer:</l>
               <l>And few remembers good turnes paſt and gone,</l>
               <l>VVhere ſuch great perſons naturall glaſſe is runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:32"/>
               <l>Could I collect together, in one ſumme,</l>
               <l>A record of the honorable deeds,</l>
               <l>Of all thoſe gifts beſtow'd, and fauours done,</l>
               <l>Which from her free and bounteous minds proceeds:</l>
               <l>Then ſhould I to ſmall purpoſe ſpend my dayes</l>
               <l>In writing that which hath no end of prayſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat bounds or limits hath her honor knowne,</l>
               <l>Or who can ſound ſo deepe, or well declare her,</l>
               <l>VVhen thoſe faire wings, ſhee flyes with, are her owne,</l>
               <l>VVhich to that mightie height of fame did reare her:</l>
               <l>I need not adde vnto the Ocean more,</l>
               <l>VVhat is one drop vnto ſuch wonderous ſtore?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas, great Ladie, thou haſt little need</l>
               <l>Of my harſh tongue to praiſe thy bountie ſo;</l>
               <l>In euery place thy fame as well doth ſpeed,</l>
               <l>And better too, then I haue power to ſhow:</l>
               <l>Thy worth by me no more diſgrace endures,</l>
               <l>Then Sun, when clouds her glorious light obſcures.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, Honorable Lady, know thy ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Although I cannot pay thee halfe thy due,</l>
               <l>But toſſed am vpon misfortune ſhelfe,</l>
               <l>And cannot ſing thy honors full, nor true:</l>
               <l>Yet from theſe aſhes may a Phaenix ſpring,</l>
               <l>VVhen they haue heard thy worth and better ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then take this vertue now into thy hand,</l>
               <l>My feeble ſpirits begin for to retire;</l>
               <l>Such power thy vertues haue, they can withſtand</l>
               <l>A better pen, and bid my thoughts admire,</l>
               <l>And glory in the ſubiect, not my Muſe,</l>
               <l>VVhich can more faults then I haue done excuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:32"/>
               <l>Yet giue me leaue a little to proceed,</l>
               <l>And ſome more graces of her minde diſcouer;</l>
               <l>My fond affection, in this vaine to feed,</l>
               <l>One vertue ſtill, you ſee, calls in another:</l>
               <l>VVhere though I doe begin, and ſpeake of many,</l>
               <l>Yet can I finde no end of prayſing any.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy hoſpitalitie did as much renowne thee,</l>
               <l>As cannot be by mortall tongues expreſt;</l>
               <l>And with as great deſarts and prayſes crowne thee,</l>
               <l>Filling thee with more glory then the reſt:</l>
               <l>And brings thee forth vpon this ſtage to ſhow thee</l>
               <l>VVhat thy deſarts and their affections owe thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy ſpeaking praiſe from Cottage to the Throne,</l>
               <l>Attend thee, Ladie, with no common glorie;</l>
               <l>Thy bounteous deeds ſo ſpred abroad and knowne,</l>
               <l>VVrites in mens hearts thy neuer dying ſtorie;</l>
               <l>VVhere it ſhall liue paſt all ſucceeding ages,</l>
               <l>As willing pen and vertue true preſages.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy bounteous table kept, who may declare,</l>
               <l>Or greatneſſe of thy hoſpitalitie,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe liberall minde no coſt at all doth ſpare,</l>
               <l>To grace thy honor with more dignitie?</l>
               <l>VVhere ouerwhelmed with affections ſtore,</l>
               <l>Shee to her friends thinkes greateſt bountie poore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat long enduring houſe hath honor kept,</l>
               <l>And with thy bounteous cheere, and wondrous ſtore</l>
               <l>Fed many mouthes; whil'ſt ſome haue baſely ſlept</l>
               <l>In <hi>Mammons</hi> armes, ſtill coueting more and more:</l>
               <l>Snorting in mines of gold, feeding their ſoules</l>
               <l>VVith that, the beſt, and worthieſt mindes controlls.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:33"/>
               <l>VVhich loues to heare the fall of honor true,</l>
               <l>And enuie thoſe rare gifts they doe poſſeſſe;</l>
               <l>Detracting thoſe which bounteous deeds enſue,</l>
               <l>And yet theſe ſlaues will creepe and be their gueſts;</l>
               <l>To all thoſe famous houſes, which they heare</l>
               <l>Doe keepe vp bountie, and maintaine good cheere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhil'ſt they doe ſcrape and gleane, what they can get</l>
               <l>From Bounties hands, and liberall diſpoſitions,</l>
               <l>VVhich ne're a good houſe kept themſelues as yet,</l>
               <l>Nor ne're will doe, ſo baſe are their conditions:</l>
               <l>If they can creepe but into honors fauours,</l>
               <l>Theile feede and burſt vpon anothers labours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus from great perſons free, and bounteous tables,</l>
               <l>They heape vp wealth by wretched miſerie,</l>
               <l>And make their heires ſo ſtrong in meanes, and able;</l>
               <l>That in the compaſſe of gentilitie</l>
               <l>They muſt be drawne and honored of ſome men,</l>
               <l>Although their fathers baſely begg'd for them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I doe not vrge this, moſt renowned Lady,</l>
               <l>Though many men haue bettered beene by thee,</l>
               <l>To ayme or point at any thing, that may be</l>
               <l>Thought preiudiciall to thy dignitie:</l>
               <l>But as thou art moſt liberall, free and kinde,</l>
               <l>So to expreſſe the bountie of thy minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now can the Citie, Countrie, and the Court,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe eares haue heard of thy diſperſed fame,</l>
               <l>Vnto thy Princely Palace make reſort,</l>
               <l>And fill their thoughts with thy admired name:</l>
               <l>VVhere hearts, eyes, eares, and all deſires to proue</l>
               <l>The great magnificence of thy grace and loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:33"/>
               <l>VVith curteous, kinde, and honor'd diſpoſitions,</l>
               <l>Such as is wont in noble breſts to dwell,</l>
               <l>Thou entertaines great birthes, and faire conditions</l>
               <l>VVith ſuch rare grace and geſtures as excell:</l>
               <l>No wiſe conceits, nor curious Artiſt found,</l>
               <l>But for thy courteous grace thy praiſes found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No worthy Lady, of the nobleſt ſtraine,</l>
               <l>VVhich for her parts and wiſdome was diuine;</l>
               <l>But thou with bounteous hand did'ſt entertaine</l>
               <l>And ſhow thy ſelfe as free as <hi>Caeſars</hi> minde:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe ſalutations were as fairely dreſt,</l>
               <l>And powdred with the wiſdome of the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heere greatneſſe doth another greatneſſe grace;</l>
               <l>Loue meetes with loue, heere honor, honor kiſſes;</l>
               <l>Heere noble mindes each other doe embrace,</l>
               <l>Nought to make vp ſuch ſweete contentment miſſes:</l>
               <l>So faire a troupe of worthy perſons meeting,</l>
               <l>But few haue ſeene in ſuch great honor greeting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here liberall <hi>Ceres</hi> plaies no niggards part,</l>
               <l>Here Heau'n, earth, Seas their greateſt plenty brings,</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Bacchus</hi> cheeres the melancholly heart,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt a learn'd conſort of ſweete Muſicke ſings:</l>
               <l>A feaſt that did more ſumptuous coſt afford,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Cleopatra</hi> did that noble Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who hath beene fam'd for hoſpitalitie,</l>
               <l>That hath not ranckt her name among the reſt?</l>
               <l>Who haue for bountie and for dignitie</l>
               <l>Admired beene, and left her vnexpreſt?</l>
               <l>Who hath a worthier houſe kept all her daies</l>
               <l>Then ſhe hath done, and liu'd in greater praiſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:34"/>
               <l>No, Lady, though our Shire did thee containe,</l>
               <l>Yet are thy honors and thy bountie ſpred;</l>
               <l>And can as great a ſhare and glorie claime,</l>
               <l>As theirs can doe, and grace thee being dead:</l>
               <l>With true deſeruing fame, for euer bleſt,</l>
               <l>To equall <hi>Pellam, Ramſey,</hi> and the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No niggards hand, nor greedy gaine did hold her,</l>
               <l>The nobleſt mindes are not in loue with riches,</l>
               <l>Nor haue her vertues for ſuch trifles ſold her,</l>
               <l>Though many great ones powerfull gold bewitches:</l>
               <l>But what meanes heere the heauens her freely lent,</l>
               <l>Shee waſteth nor, though liberally ſhee ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to a better end and purpoſe vſde them,</l>
               <l>The hungrie members of our Lord to feed,</l>
               <l>And not in ſuch diſordred ſort abus'd them,</l>
               <l>But help'd the weake afflicted in their need</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to refreſh the brethren poore,</l>
               <l>Which ſtands and waits for charitie at the doore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her yerning pitie did ſo farre extend,</l>
               <l>That deepe compaſſion ſhee did on them take,</l>
               <l>And in their great neceſſities did befriend</l>
               <l>Their ſoules and bodies for meere charities ſake:</l>
               <l>With gifts and good rewards ſhee did ſupplie</l>
               <l>Their extreame wants, and ſau'd them like to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How many hath ſhee eas'd of <hi>Lazars</hi> crue,</l>
               <l>The pooreſt members of our dying Lord,</l>
               <l>Whoſe great diſtreſſe the kindeſt natures rue,</l>
               <l>Toſt to and fro, and in this world abhorr'd:</l>
               <l>Deſpis'd and made a ſcorne of euery eye,</l>
               <l>Which doth behold their woe and miſery.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:34"/>
               <l>Thus doe they ſhow from whence they are deſcended,</l>
               <l>From that old ſerpent their adopted father,</l>
               <l>Which neuer will, nor euer haue extended</l>
               <l>The leaſt reliefe, as <hi>Diues</hi> crummes to gather;</l>
               <l>His dogs were kinder for to licke his ſores,</l>
               <l>Then me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are now, which beats them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their dores.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou, great Lady, wherein vertue reſted,</l>
               <l>Did'ſt daily feed them at thy bounteous gate,</l>
               <l>And the poore members of Chriſts flocke haſt feaſted,</l>
               <l>Comiſerating heere their wofull ſtate,</l>
               <l>Which nothing haue in this world to relieue them,</l>
               <l>But what ſuch liberall minds as yours doth giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poore naked wormes which feele the ſharpeſt aire,</l>
               <l>Which wants food, cloth, and home, which many haue,</l>
               <l>What is heere left to keepe yee from deſpaire,</l>
               <l>When all your hopes and comforts are the graue:</l>
               <l>And if it were not for ſome worthie mindes,</l>
               <l>Your ſoules would faint and die before your times.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou, moſt true deuoted Ladie, giues</l>
               <l>Both cloth, food, harbour, to ſuch orphanes poore,</l>
               <l>And helpeſt thoſe which in extremities liue,</l>
               <l>And ne're expuls'd the needie from thy doore:</l>
               <l>But at the point of death their ſoules did cheriſh,</l>
               <l>And ſau'd thoſe liues which ready were to periſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus did thy faith beare ſweete and pleaſant fruits,</l>
               <l>Which euer from that flouriſhing tree proceeds,</l>
               <l>VVith ſuch rich graces, as beſt honor ſutes,</l>
               <l>And did extend it ſelfe to bounteous deeds:</l>
               <l>Relieuing cheerefully thoſe ſilly elues,</l>
               <l>VVhich had no meanes here for to help themſelues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:35"/>
               <l>Thou faire example liue without compare,</l>
               <l>Thou map of honor be for euer bleſt,</l>
               <l>Since to the poore ſuch pitty thou doſt beare,</l>
               <l>Which meaner perſons in their pride deteſt,</l>
               <l>And doſt extend thy hand to helpe their neede,</l>
               <l>Whilſt their fell cruelties make their harts to bleede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay not contented thus, thou lefts behinde,</l>
               <l>As long as any age or time indures,</l>
               <l>A faire example of thy bounteous minde,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall for euer ſtand moſt firme and ſure,</l>
               <l>Where thou haſt meanes, and liuing left in ſtore,</l>
               <l>To helpe the helpeleſſe, and releiue the poore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Could I but reckon what her honor gaue,</l>
               <l>Or what a number at her gate ſhe fed;</l>
               <l>How many needie wretches liues ſhe ſau'd,</l>
               <l>For want of foode halfe pinde and almoſt dead,</l>
               <l>The ſum I feare would grow ſo wondrous large,</l>
               <l>And far extend my weakeneſſe to diſcharge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No 'tis not to be told with any tongue,</l>
               <l>Thoſe great accounts my pen muſt let alone,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe attempting I ſhould doe her wrong,</l>
               <l>To take away from her what is her owne,</l>
               <l>For numberleſſe they are, and ſo I'le leaue them,</l>
               <l>Where endleſſe ioyes for endles good receiue them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For what ſhe gaue to thoſe, ſhe lent to him,</l>
               <l>VVhich will repay't againe vnto a penny:</l>
               <l>She ſhall not looſe by that ſhe knowes, but win,</l>
               <l>And crowned be in heauen, with ioyes as many,</l>
               <l>VVhere double recompence ſhe ſhall ſurely haue,</l>
               <l>And thouſand fold more finde then here ſhe gaue,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:35"/>
               <l>Her goods poſſeſſing ſhe did not poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>But made them free for others which did neede them,</l>
               <l>They were not hers ſhe often would confeſſe:</l>
               <l>But lent her to refreſh the poore, and feede them,</l>
               <l>Where ſhe as tenant held from his great hands,</l>
               <l>All that ſhe did poſſeſſe, both goods and lands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And knew right well that ſhe account muſt giue,</l>
               <l>Of all thoſe rich demeanes ſhe here inioyd,</l>
               <l>And in ſo great a calling how ſhe liue,</l>
               <l>Vnto what vſe her Talent was imployd,</l>
               <l>Where now with that good ſeruant ſhe doth finde,</l>
               <l>Her maſters ioy and ten times more aſſignde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh Lady why doe I this vertue vrge,</l>
               <l>So much in thee and cannot finde in others,</l>
               <l>Art thou alone vnto theſe times a ſcourge,</l>
               <l>To whip their dulneſſe forward, and diſcouer?</l>
               <l>Thoſe monſtrous wolues which neuer will be fed,</l>
               <l>But eate vp pooreſt Orphants like to bred.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Religion is the cauſe of this I hold,</l>
               <l>That to good workes will not aſcribe ſaluation,</l>
               <l>Which makes our age in charitie grow ſo cold,</l>
               <l>As few will giue becauſe 'tis out of faſhion,</l>
               <l>Then let our works be meritorious found,</l>
               <l>It may be then more charity will abound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus doth this topſie-turuie age delight</l>
               <l>In contraries, and leaues the good vndon,</l>
               <l>Wrong hath the vpper hand of truth and right,</l>
               <l>And euery man to ſwift perdition runs:</l>
               <l>If this ſaluation were, as none it is,</l>
               <l>Who would be damn'd then that ſhould doe amiſſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:36"/>
               <l>But, world, thy ſhare will come farre ſhort, I feare,</l>
               <l>For vain's that hope, whoſe faith brings forth no fruit,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhowes it ſelfe in vertuous actions here,</l>
               <l>What's better for a tongue if one be mute:</l>
               <l>Or for that riſe which breeds a greater fall,</l>
               <l>Or for that faith which ſhowes no workes at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good Lady, thou which did'ſt poſſeſſe ſo much,</l>
               <l>And ſpent'ſt ſo little vpon idle pleaſure;</l>
               <l>How farre doeſt thou digreſſe from theſe I touch,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke to ſtore thy ſoule with better treaſures?</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſecret graces which the heau'ns impart</l>
               <l>To ſuch as be vpright, and true of heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where zeale, grace, faith, loue, hope and pietie,</l>
               <l>Concurre in one to make a bleſſed ſoule;</l>
               <l>Where temperance, bountie, and humilitie,</l>
               <l>Doe all foule Vice, and errors falſe controule:</l>
               <l>Where her renowned hoſpitalitie,</l>
               <l>Makes her moſt happie, ioyn'd with charitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where with that worthy Captaine well ſhee ſpeeds,</l>
               <l>Nor feares ſhee death, that freely is forgiuen;</l>
               <l>Her prayers, gifts, rewards, and almeſdeeds,</l>
               <l>Are now remembred in the ſight of heauen:</l>
               <l>Where ſhee doth heare the voice of him ſhee lou'd,</l>
               <l>Which hath her faith through ſuch affliction prou'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And where her workes, and deeds, and vertues all,</l>
               <l>Attends her after this expired breath,</l>
               <l>And did not ſuffer her great name to fall</l>
               <l>Into obliuion, by forgetfull death:</l>
               <l>But breakes thoſe priſon doores, and ſweetly ſings,</l>
               <l>Hell, where's thy victorie? Death, where's thy ſting?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:36"/>
               <l>Thou fore-decreed by that eternall doome,</l>
               <l>A ſacred veſſell of moſt free election,</l>
               <l>A marke of pietie to the times to come,</l>
               <l>Seal'd with heau'ns finger at thy firſt conception:</l>
               <l>Grac'd with his grace, which doth all grace ſecure,</l>
               <l>VVhich time conſumes not, but doth ſtill endure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke when as <hi>Tytan</hi> from his ſcarlet bed</l>
               <l>Doth riſe, and all thicke vapors driue away,</l>
               <l>And all the curtaines of the heau'ns are ſpred,</l>
               <l>VVithout a cloud to blemiſh any way,</l>
               <l>Where that bright frame to mortalls doth appeare</l>
               <l>Moſt wondrous calme, moſt perfect, faire &amp; cleare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Euen ſo this riſing Sunne of honor ſhines,</l>
               <l>The hopefull ſigne of a moſt glorious day,</l>
               <l>And all the graces firmely ſo combines,</l>
               <l>That miſts, nor clouds, nor vapors can diſmay:</l>
               <l>This faire vnblemiſh'd frame keepes ſtill true honor,</l>
               <l>Which Time, Death, Fortune, neuer ſhal take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What man ſo great in pompe and earthly glorie,</l>
               <l>That hunts full crie with hungrie breath for fame,</l>
               <l>Can write inſuing ſinnes a fairer ſtorie,</l>
               <l>Or win more honor, or a grater name:</l>
               <l>Or graces be with more deſarts and prayſe,</l>
               <l>Then ſhee had beene ſo truely all her dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe that in the full circuite ride of pride,</l>
               <l>Liu'd in a world of eyes for to behold them:</l>
               <l>Had what this earth could grace them with beſide,</l>
               <l>And at the higheſt riſe of fame hath ſold them:</l>
               <l>Made all their words and deeds like <hi>Herods</hi> then,</l>
               <l>Which cried the voice of God, and not of men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:37"/>
               <l>Yet in the mid'ſt of all their pride deceiued,</l>
               <l>Haue brought their honor to vntimely ends,</l>
               <l>And of their golden hopes haue bene bereaued,</l>
               <l>VVhich with the world would die ſuch mighty freinds.</l>
               <l>Their miſtris with <hi>vae vobis</hi> leaues them all,</l>
               <l>VVhen they doe leaſt dreame, and ſuſpect to fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But they which build their houſe one vertues ground,</l>
               <l>And leade that life which thou before haſt done,</l>
               <l>No age no fortune euer ſhall confound,</l>
               <l>Their honors when their naturall glaſſe is run,</l>
               <l>But they ſhall flouriſh faire and ſtill ſuruiue.</l>
               <l>Death takes not them like thoſe which dye, aliue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus hauing looſ'd theeſe earthly fetters here,</l>
               <l>That heauie bondage worſe then Egipts thrall,</l>
               <l>And ouercome by faith thoſe doubts and feares,</l>
               <l>VVhich greues the beſt, and doth in queſtion call,</l>
               <l>Our liues and deeds with many frailties ſhaken:</l>
               <l>How ſhal we ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d when ſuch ſtrict reckonings taken?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But fly to the heauens true and onely ſonne,</l>
               <l>Deere Sauiour and redeemer whoſe ſtrong might,</l>
               <l>Di'dſt that huge blacke internall hoſt orecome,</l>
               <l>And put thoſe powers, and enemies all to flight.</l>
               <l>That conquereſt quite, hell, ſathan, death, and ſin,</l>
               <l>VVhich none before, nor ſince could euer win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And open ſets the doore t'eternall life,</l>
               <l>Freed vs from all our enemies by thy death;</l>
               <l>Although we ſuffer toyle, cares, greefe, and ſtrife,</l>
               <l>VVithin our ſelues during this mortall breath:</l>
               <l>Yet when thou thinkeſt good thou wilt inlarge vs,</l>
               <l>And of our weary, heauie load diſcharge vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:37"/>
               <l>Whereof being freed, and ſet at liberty,</l>
               <l>Thou endleſſe ioyes for ending greefe imbraceſt,</l>
               <l>And di'ſt no more but liu'ſt eternally,</l>
               <l>With him from whom thou haſt bene euer grac'd,</l>
               <l>Where now enioying what thou wantedſt here,</l>
               <l>Thou ſing'ſt <hi>Halluiah</hi> with that heauenly quire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where, now vnto that glory I will leaue thee,</l>
               <l>That true felicity, and eternall reſt,</l>
               <l>Which like to earthly ioyes, will not deceiue thee,</l>
               <l>But ſtill indure effectuall and ere bleſt,</l>
               <l>Triumphing with thoſe Saints which euer ſings,</l>
               <l>All praiſe and glory to the King of Kings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here noble Lord ſome vertues of your owne,</l>
               <l>May in this darke, and little glaſſe appeare,</l>
               <l>Or of that ſeede which you your ſelfe are ſowne,</l>
               <l>Which cannot (like your honors) ſhine ſo cleare,</l>
               <l>Yet may you ſee ſome ſhaddow of your fauour,</l>
               <l>If that you truely doe but read my labour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For in this little booke I haue not err'd,</l>
               <l>Although her honors worth I could not weild,</l>
               <l>Nor vice before true vertue haue prefer'd,</l>
               <l>Nor yet on ſuch falſe ſlipperie grounds doe build,</l>
               <l>As grace a ſin by a diſſembling tongue,</l>
               <l>To doe the beſt, and nobleſt natures wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No let me neuer riſe but rather fall,</l>
               <l>If lower then I am I can deſcend,</l>
               <l>When euer I take vices part at all,</l>
               <l>Or ayme at any ſuch vaine hopes or end,</l>
               <l>But rather ſtudy vertuouſly to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Then haue my duty ſicke of that diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:38"/>
               <l>No, worthy Lord, Ile neuer ſell my ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Though I ſhould be farre poorer then I am,</l>
               <l>By vniuſt meanes to purchaſe worldly pelfe,</l>
               <l>As ſooth vp folly in the greateſt man:</l>
               <l>That gaine is loſſe, that glory turnes to ſhame,</l>
               <l>Which branded is with <hi>Gnato's</hi> flattering name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then let not honor iudge my liues amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Although your iudgement farre extends my verſe,</l>
               <l>My duty's true, and ſo ſhall proue by this,</l>
               <l>Which I vnworthy farre, haue heere rehearſt:</l>
               <l>If I in ought through weakneſſe haue offended,</l>
               <l>Let greatneſſe by their faire acceptance mend it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For I doe know two noble natures ſpringing,</l>
               <l>From one pure fountaine cannot be diuided;</l>
               <l>What wrong to her, to you ſome blot is bringing,</l>
               <l>Which cannot be but by your worth decided:</l>
               <l>For you that doe ſucceed her roome and place,</l>
               <l>Are heire vnto her vertues and her grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe faire example happie you may proue,</l>
               <l>And like a greater light the leſſer guide,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with honor, glorie, grace and loue,</l>
               <l>And bleſt with all theſe earthly things beſide:</l>
               <l>That wanting nought to fill vp eithers ſtore,</l>
               <l>Your honor ſtill may flouriſh more and more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who takes a patterne of his glorious maker,</l>
               <l>And ſeekes to treade the tract of honor true,</l>
               <l>Cannot at firſt be made a full partaker</l>
               <l>Of all thoſe rich demeanes, to honor due:</l>
               <l>Such faire examples muſt haue time and ſpace</l>
               <l>To ouertake them, 'tis no common race.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:38"/>
               <l>Which ſhee, true vertues patterne, left behinde,</l>
               <l>Much like a marble pillar vnremou'd,</l>
               <l>Such tokens of her honorable minde,</l>
               <l>As make her heere generally belou'd:</l>
               <l>Whereof when you ſhall take a fuller view,</l>
               <l>Shall finde thoſe honors fall to th'houſe and you.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where I doe pray that heau'ns would grace it ſtill,</l>
               <l>With as great honor as it had before;</l>
               <l>Or greater, if it be his bleſſed will,</l>
               <l>Vntill the ſurges ouerflow the ſhore:</l>
               <l>That <hi>Wentworths</hi> noble race with <hi>Cheauies</hi> name,</l>
               <l>May be inrol'd in euerlaſting fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And you, faire Lady, grac'd with Natures gifts,</l>
               <l>And with a ſpirit that hath true vertue in it;</l>
               <l>Which my deiected Muſe from ſorrowes lifts,</l>
               <l>And hath more power, then others haue to win it:</l>
               <l>Bound with a dutie which muſt not be broken,</l>
               <l>Giuen at my firſt conception for a token.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You the true Image of that Lady great,</l>
               <l>For vertue and an honorable minde,</l>
               <l>Of whom for your faire worth I would intreate,</l>
               <l>More then affection doth in others binde:</l>
               <l>To whom I owe more then you deigne to craue,</l>
               <l>Loue, ſeruice, dutie, life and all I haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A preſent all too meane if 'twere farre better,</l>
               <l>In one whom meaneneſſe, meaneneſſe doth excell,</l>
               <l>To whom I muſt and will remaine a debter;</l>
               <l>A debter great, how great I cannot tell:</l>
               <l>Whoſe many fauours ſhow'd to friends and me,</l>
               <l>Lies hid within, that cannot vttered be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:39"/>
               <l>VVhat ſhall I giue, that nothing haue to paie,</l>
               <l>The widowes mite will not paſſe currant now,</l>
               <l>That metall's growne nought with vs now adaies,</l>
               <l>Nor is it for true currant pay allow'd.</l>
               <l>Yet where there's nothing to be had you finde,</l>
               <l>Accept, good Lady, of a gratefull minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This worke to your pure minde I doe preſent,</l>
               <l>This honors prize vnto thy Iudgement ſound;</l>
               <l>VVhere if for any fault I ſhould be ſhent,</l>
               <l>Let ſome defence in thee be had and found:</l>
               <l>Leſt if ſome tempeſt ſhould ariſe too faſt,</l>
               <l>I ſhould be ſhiprack'd, or in danger caſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For well I know you lou'd her honor liuing,</l>
               <l>Intirely ſo, as pen cannot declare,</l>
               <l>And after death in true affections giuing,</l>
               <l>Did'ſt loue and zeale ſtill to her honor beare:</l>
               <l>Then for her ſake let theſe ſome fauour finde,</l>
               <l>That was her ſelfe ſo courteous, free and kinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good Lady, which her life haſt ſeene and knowne,</l>
               <l>And all her vertues and her honors proued,</l>
               <l>To whom her thoughts, and counſels all were ſhowne,</l>
               <l>So much was you, and ſhee of you beloued:</l>
               <l>Can better tell what ſtore of vertues lie</l>
               <l>Hid in her breſt, which no man can deſcrie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I doe but adde a droppe vnto the ſea,</l>
               <l>For who can comprehend in any bounds</l>
               <l>Her honor 'tis but labour caſt away,</l>
               <l>To finde out that, which is not to be found:</l>
               <l>But as a ſparke is to a mightie fire,</l>
               <l>So muſt I yeeld and valew my deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:39"/>
               <l>And though her modeſt bluſhes will not let her,</l>
               <l>Her vertues prize, nor take what is her owne,</l>
               <l>Nor with that true deſeruing praiſe beſet her,</l>
               <l>VVhich to the world is blaz'd ſo much and knowne:</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall her vertues in their force abide,</l>
               <l>Which through her modeſt vaile ſhee ſought to hide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For what can heart deſire, ſhee hath not found?</l>
               <l>If wealth or riches ſhee hath not leaſt ſtore,</l>
               <l>If fame or praiſe, her name with that doth ſound,</l>
               <l>If honor, who, for her eſtate, had more?</l>
               <l>If with long life, or length of daies and time,</l>
               <l>VVho longer liu'd, whoſe honor more did ſhine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If with the gifts or graces of the minde,</l>
               <l>VVho with her almoſt now may well compare,</l>
               <l>Or hath had more, or better beene inclinde,</l>
               <l>VVhich kept her vertues with the faireſt faire:</l>
               <l>And like that praiſe, which Scriptures <hi>Dauid</hi> gaue,</l>
               <l>Brought good old age and honor to her graue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus in this little volume may you reade,</l>
               <l>Some vertues of her honorable minde,</l>
               <l>Some of her merits, worthie parts and deeds,</l>
               <l>For all it is vnpoſſible to finde</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe that I ſhould out of nature dwell,</l>
               <l>And learne ſuch notes, which humane notes excell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus hoping of your gratious cenſures all,</l>
               <l>I leaue yee to that euerlaſting bliſſe,</l>
               <l>'Twas fate, not wit, which to this taske did call</l>
               <l>My meaner ſpirits, and rays'd my minde to this:</l>
               <l>If ought miſcaries blame not my intent,</l>
               <l>For what is rudely ſung, is better meant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:2720:40"/>
               <l>To which pure, ſacred, bleſſed Trinitie,</l>
               <l>Which rules vnſeene all things for th'beſt aboue vs,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Perſons three inclos'd ith vnitie;</l>
               <l>A wonder ſtrange, yet not ſo ſtrange to loue vs:</l>
               <l>Being ſuch ſinners 'gainſt his Lawes rebelling,</l>
               <l>Paſt all the tongues of men and Angels telling;</l>
               <l>To him in all and vnto all in one.</l>
               <l>Be all praiſe, powre and glorie giuen alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2720:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
